This week, we've done a wide sweep through
some of the deepest aspects of learning.
Metaphors and analogies aren't just for
art and literature.
One of the best things you can do to not
only remember but more easily understand
concepts in many different fields, is to
create a metaphor or analogy for them.
Often the more visual, the better.
We've learned from Nobel prize winner
Santiago Ramón y Cajal that
if you change your thoughts, you can
really truly change your life.
It seems people can enhance the
development of their
neuronal circuits by practicing thoughts
that use those neurons.
Like Santiago Ramon y Cajal, you can take
pride in aiming for success
because of the very things that make other
people say you can't do it.
Keep in mind that when you whiz through a
homework or test question and you don't go
back
to check your work, you're acting a little
like a
person who's refusing to use parts of your
brain.
You're not stopping to take a mental
breath and then revisit what you've
done with the bigger picture in mind to
see whether it makes sense.
Overconfidence in your results can result
from using only one mode of thinking.
By making it a point to do some of your
studying with
friends, you can more easily catch where
your thinking has gone astray.
Taking a test is serious business.
Just as fighter pilots and doctors go
through checklists before takeoff and
surgery,
going through your own test preparation
checklist
can vastly improve your chances of
success.
Counterintuitive strategies, such as the
hard start
jump to easy technique, can give your
brain
a chance to reflect on harder challenges,
even
as you're focusing on other, more
straightforward problems.
Here are some last test-taking pointers.
The body puts out chemicals when it's
under stress.
How you interpret your body's reaction to
those chemicals makes all the difference.
If you shift your thinking from this test
has made me afraid to this
test has got me excited to do my best, it
helps improve your performance.
If you're panicked on a test, momentarily
turn your attention to your breathing.
Relax your stomach.
Place your hand on it and slowly draw a
deep breath.
Your hand should move outward and your
whole chest should expand like a barrel.
Your mind can trick you into thinking that
what you've done is correct, even if it
isn't.
This means that whenever possible, you
should blink, shift your attention,
and then double check your answers using a
big picture perspective.
Asking yourself, does this really make
sense?
And finally, remember, that not getting
enough sleep the night
before a test can negate any other
preparation you've done.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning about learning.