John G Maguire comes from a family
of news reporters and writers.
His father, the late, John Maguire, wrote
for the Albany, New York Times Union.
His brother, Gregory Maguire is
a novelist whose work includes the book,
Wicked, from which a hit
musical has been made.
John Maguire has been
a professional writer all his life.
He began in college as a physics major but
switched before graduation to
studying English literature.
He then pursued a career as
a newspaper science writer.
He's covered science news for three daily
newspapers in the US, was nominated for
a Pulitzer Prize in Journalism,
and has written several books.
He's also taught writing for
many years at Boston area colleges.
When John was teaching at the Berkeley
College of Music, he invented a new
approach to help sometimes confused and
worried students to write well.
It's called the readability method.
It was published by the Education
Department of Newsweek Magazine.
His latest version of this approach is
described in his College Writing Guide.
John has a Bachelors and
a Master of Fine Arts degree in English.
He currently has an editing business and
teaches writing at Middlesex Community
College in Bedford, Massachusetts.
Let's welcome John Maguire.
John, you wrote a wonderful article for
the Atlantic.
The Secret to Good Writing,
it's about objects, not ideas.
This is pretty counter-intuitive for
a lot of people.
I mean, most of us have been
brought up to think that writing is
all about the good ideas.
So, can you explain what you meant?
>> Yes, Barbara, it does seem strange for
a writing teacher to
say think about objects more than
you're thinking about ideas.
Of course,
it is important to write about ideas.
But my point in that article was to say,
it's easy
to express ideas in terms of objects.
And what a good writer thinks
about is what objects can
I use to express my ideas?
It's not bad to use idea words, but
it's easy to get overrun with idea
words and use too many of them.
You can become over-abstract, and when
your writing becomes over-abstract, and
there are too many I-O-N words or
T-I-O-N words in a given passage.
It becomes very hard for
the reader to know what's going on.
And in fact, the writer often gets
confused about what he or she is saying.
When things become very abstract, they
become very blurry, and both the reader
and the writer has to spend a lot of time
figuring out what the heck is being said.
The point I wanted to make is that
all ideas are related to objects.
Let me show a diagram.
Here on a white board is what we
call the ladder of abstractions.
This is a ladder that runs
from low to high, and
at the top end of the ladder are abstract
ideas, let's say, the idea of nutrition.
Now, an abstract idea is a non-physical
thing that you cannot touch.
At the bottom of the ladder are, connected
to the word nutrition, actual things like
apples, oranges, slices of bread,
hamburger sandwiches.
Any idea that you're trying to get across,
let us say you're writing about good
nutrition for pregnant women,
can be communicated in terms of things.
And the principle that writers follow is,
when you're writing about ideas, go down
the ladder to the world of things and
make you sure write with enough things.
>> So, in our course, we suggest to
learners that they should alternate
between sort of close in focus and
a more diffuse approach to learning in
order to learn something difficult.
So toggling between a tight
intent sort of attention and
a loose sort of attention
seems to really work.
You've told me that professional writers
seem to do the same sort of switching.
Can you tell us how a writer switches
between focused and relaxed thinking?
>> Any creative person switches from
one mode to another frequently.
Maybe the best example
of this is painters.
The classic, cliche image of a painter is
somebody who is up close to the canvas,
putting a little dot of paint on.
And then,
he backs up halfway across the room,
takes a look at what the effect has been
of that dot of paint, thinks about it,
weighs it, goes back in, puts some
more dots of paint on the painting.
The shifting of focus from up close to far
back is obvious in the world of a painter.
You have spoken about how important
that is in the world of math.
And how, when you are leaning equations,
it's a good idea to come in close, and
really master what you need to know and
sometimes it's a good idea to
pull back in order to understand the
problems that you have to solve with math.
Writers switch focus many different ways.
Sometimes you will turn from
what you are trying to say and
you'll talk to your friends and ask your
friends what they know about the subject.
That broadens out the discussion
of what you're trying to say.
Sometimes you will shift and
do a little bit of reading.
Maybe go on Wikipedia for
five minutes to look up some material that
relates to what you're talking about.
Sometime you will shift writing on
a computer to writing longhand.
I sometimes shift from writing while
sitting down to writing while standing up.
And of course, there's the tried and
true, let's take a walk around the block.
Charles Dickens did it and if he did it,
it's good enough for me and for
college writers, I would say.
>> I see.
So beyond concrete nouns or
things, what other advice do
you give your students about what
they should put into their writing?
Barbara, writing well is a matter
of choosing a good style, and
style is basically the choice of what kind
of words are you going to write with.
What parameters are you
going to have control over?
So beyond putting in things,
which is very important,
I tell my students, put in active verbs.
These are verbs that make
something happen on the page.
I also tell them to put in people.
How do you put people
into a piece of writing?
You name them.
Full name or nickname, name some people.
Put them into your writing.
Use some active verbs.
Make things happen on the page.
Other pieces of advice I suggest are,
use short words when you can instead
of long ones, and use short sentences.
It's often important, especially for
beginning writers, not to let their
sentences get out of control too long.
When in doubt, write it short.
>> Have you ever taught students for
whom English was their second language?
What can you tell a student who has
learned to write outside an English
speaking country?
>> Yes, I have taught people to
write who were ESL speakers.
One of the more interesting friends I made
recently was a young man named Saktai.
I taught him last semester
in the city of Lowell.
The first papers he turned in
were really pretty terrible.
I asked him why he wrote that way and
he told me he had been taught to
write that way by his teacher
back in I think it was Vietnam.
And I said, you are out of control
with what you're saying here.
You have to be simpler.
And he told me that his teacher had told
him, make sure you use your long words and
show people that you're educated.
That's the way to write.
And, I said to him Saktai,
that's not the way we do it in English.
In English, we really favor the plain
style, which means clear and simple.
So I'm going to give you some advice,
young man,
I said, trying to get his attention.
I want you to stop trying to be impressive
and just start trying to be clear.
I had to say it a couple of times.
And I told him this, I said, once you are
clear then you're going to be impressive.
So stop trying to be impressive,
just work on being completely clear.
About four weeks later,
his writing had improved quite a bit, and,
he came to me and
said that the advice that I had
given him to stop trying to be impressive
and just to be clear had really worked.
Nobody had ever told him that before,
he really needed to hear it.
Now he understood what he had to do, and
he felt much more powerful as a writer.
Instead of trying to do two things
at once, which was to be clear and
to be impressive,
he just tried to be clear.
And as we both know, when you read
something that is really clear,
after you finish reading it you say,
wow, that was impressive.
And that's the way it works,
clarity first.
>> [LAUGH] What a great point.
It is funny, when I, I read research
papers, I can always tell a difference
between the second tier, the sort of
lower caliber research papers and
the upper tier research papers, because
the lower caliber ones are often fuzzy.
They use a lot of big words.
They're hard to read.
They're hard to understand.
But the ones that really are top notch,
they're often so
simple and so elegantly written.
And, and you, you might say, well, you
know, that's not academic writing because
it's too elegant, but that's actually the
very best of writing in any discipline.
So some teachers,
let me ask you about this.
Some teachers tell students
not to edit as they
write because they think it's a bad idea.
How do you feel about that?
>> I agree with those coaches who say
separate the writing from the editing.
Writing is a matter of getting things down
on the paper, or on the screen rapidly.
You want to maintain
rapid forward progress.
You don't want to get stuck and
lose your momentum.
Editing is a process of being judgmental,
deciding whether things are working.
And if you're not a very good writer, if
you're a beginning writer, it's possible
to produce a bad sentence and then be
totally stymied about how to fix it,
and spend minutes puzzling over
something stupid that you've written.
Far better to choose to maintain
your momentum, roll forward.
You want to get the conveyor
belt of ideas rolling.
After lots of material that's
come out of your idea factory and
your writing factory,
then you can change gears and edit.
I have another idea about editing
which is that it's often useful to
print out a draft and edit on paper.
I do that.
I think a great many professional writers
will print out a draft, edit it on paper,
and then enter their edits back into
the computer version of the text.
>> That sounds like great advice.
I know for me, when I'm writing and
I find myself really getting stuck,
it's generally because I'm starting
to edit while I'm writing.
And so often I'll find that I,
if I just let go and let it come out,
later on, mostly I find it's not as bad
as I thought when I was writing it.
because usually when it comes out,
I'm thinking oh, it's terrible.
But it comes out and it, and I do
a little tweaking and it's not too bad.
So suppose a student really
wants to write better.
Is there some special technique of reading
that will help improve your writing?
>> Well,
read closely the people you admire.
If you're writing short stories,
read the short stories you admire.
But if you're writing scientific papers or
term papers,
things to be published in journals,
read the writers whom you admire.
If there is somebody who is great in your
field and he has produced very interesting
papers that read well,
your job is to study what he or she did.
I would recommend looking closely at
the openings of papers that you like.
Perhaps, copying the opening
paragraph down longhand.
I would also recommend, underlining words
that he uses that you might not use but
you can consider using.
I would recommend you study
your writer's sentence length.
How long are his sentences?
What is the pattern of long sentences and
short sentences that your hero uses?
I would recommend looking for a sentence
that he wrote that you would think you
could never write because it's not
in your nature, and then go and
write that sentence out
longhand a couple of times.
Study what you admire.
>> So what if you're writing
a paper on a scientific
topic which focuses around
something like molecules?
They're too small to be
dropped on your foot.
How can you make that
somehow more concrete?
>> Good writers are always
thinking of their readers.
A good writer is thinking,
how is my reader going to understand this?
what is my reader going to see in
his head when he reads my words?
So this can produce a problem if you're
writing on a scientific topic, say,
about molecules.
After all, molecules are too
small to be dropped on your foot.
That's no excuse to stop
thinking physically.
You can, if you're writing about a simple
molecule like the molecule of water,
you can make a visual metaphor.
You know, a grapefruit with two lemons
attached to it will, can stand for H2O.
Or, you can go looking for
the physical objects that are related to
the chemical research
you're writing about.
You can put in as appropriate,
test tubes or Bunsen burners or
beakers, or spectrophotometers,
or a laboratory bench.
It's a skill to go looking for
physical correlates to your topic, but
it's a skill that you can
get good at pretty quick.
And it pays off because you always want
to give the reader something to see.
>> I think that's very helpful advice.
So, tell me now, what's more important,
the words or the ideas?
>> As far as the writer is concerned,
there are no ideas outside
of the realm of words.
Now I will grant you,
there are wordless intuitions and
little images you might get.
There are diagrams you can put on
a piece of paper to capture an idea.
But when it comes to being a writer,
your job is to make sure
everything gets down in words.
So if you were to ask me which is more
important in a paper, the words or
the ideas?
I say it's the words.
I'd say, without the right
words in the right order,
you do not have any ideas to work with.
As a writer, if you don't have it down
in a sentence, you don't have an idea.
>> Very good advice.
So, some coaches talk about the problem
of having too little to say.
What if a student writer discovers
that he or she has too little to say?
What or how can she or he deal with that?
>> I think a student who has quote,
too little to say, is usually a student
whose imagination is too narrow.
Often, it's a student who has decided
to write about an abstract topic and
has just kept focusing on the abstraction.
When a student is, seems to be devoid of
ideas, when a writer is devoid of ideas,
he or she should slow down and
brainstorm and brainstorm wildly.
Go to a piece of paper and write down
everything you know about the topic, draw
diagrams on a piece of paper, draw idea
maps or mind maps, make lists of objects.
Shift the focus, in other words.
A student who doesn't have enough
to say has often gotten too
tense in trying to say
something important.
It's a good idea to stop trying
to say something important and
just try to say something simple and
clear.
You can find your way to the simple and
clear by talking with a friend,
or by taking a walk, as I said.
Another thing to do is to write
some questions down for yourself.
You don't have to be an expert
on what you're writing about,
you just have to be clear.
Write down what puzzles you.
Write down what confuses you.
I am confused about x.
I am puzzled about how x relates to y.
Write these things down, cover several
pieces of paper with ideas and sketches.
It can even look like this.
Tape them together.
Cover a bunch of paper, with notes.
Set them down on your desk and
go out for a half an hours walk.
When you come back, start again.
You will have more ideas.
>> That's a, a, I, I like that approach.
So, do you have any final takeaways or
advice for writing students?
What's one thing a student
writer can do to write better?
>> I'll give you a couple of things
a writer can do to make things better.
In terms of readability,
I would suggest using short sentences.
A writer ought to go into his paper, and
if he has written any really
long sentences, ask himself,
do these sentences have to be this long,
and replace them with shorter sentences.
In terms of completeness,
a writer can do two things.
It's asking himself a couple of questions.
The first one is, what am I trying to say?
Did I say it clearly?
And the second one is,
what must I not leave out?
The very last question, which is,
what must I make sure not to leave out?
It's very useful.
I use it myself all the time at the,
as I get to the end of a draft.
I then ask myself, did I cover everything?
And in particular, is there anything
I must make sure not to leave out?
Often it turns out I have
left out something important.
So, those are my final words on this.
>> I think that's a helpful
approach even for me.
So, I, I just want to emphasize
how important I think good
writing actually is to
the learning process.
I often find, myself, that I really
learn something in the best way
when I attempt to write about it.
So, I think this is why
insight from people like you,
who've, who've really worked to
understand the writing process.
Here is your,
your book College Writing Guide.
It is very, very helpful.
So here, you can see clearly now.
And so I just very, very,
very much appreciate John your interview
with me here today and thank you,
we'll see you on the flip side.