Okay.
You've written a little bit about
something called the Imposter Syndrome.
What is the Imposter Syndrome?
And how can students overcome it?
>> Okay.
The Imposter Syndrome is like a tape
that plays inside people's heads.
Not just students a lot of people.
And, and the tape,
let's do it in a student context, though.
The tape is like this.
So the student is sitting in class,
looking around and thinking, boy,
these people are really good.
They get this stuff.
They can ask,
answer the teacher's questions.
They can do the homework.
You know, they can do fine on the test.
But I, the tape inside the head continues,
I'm really not.
I, they all,
I managed to fool them all over the years,
the tape goes, my friends, my family, my
teachers, into thinking that I'm this real
hotshot who belongs at this first
class university, taking engineering,
taking science, taking economics,
whatever i'm taking.
But I know better, and the tape continues.
The very next tough question I get in
class, the very next hard test that I
have to take, that's what's
going to finally, once and for all,
reveal me as the fraud, the phony,
the imposter, that I know I am.
And then, and then, what happens then,
is usually too horrifying to contemplate.
And so, at that point, the imposter
usually stops the tape, rewinds it.
>> [LAUGH].
>> Gets it going again.
And the interesting thing about that
phenomenon is how utterly common it is.
But every student playing
that tape imagines that he or
she is the only one who's doing it.
And the idea that a lot
of people are doing it,
and that hot shot in the front
row with the 4.0 average,
the tape is playing louder than
it is in anyone else's head.
It comes as a surprise to them.
And the reason that I'm so
sure about how common this phenomenon is,
is that I've given this talk
many times to students.
So I'm in an auditorium full of
students that i'm giving this talk to.
And when I get to the part about,
they all think I belong here,
but I know better,
it's like I plucked a guitar string.
There's a quiver that goes over
the entire audience, you know, and,
and eyes dilated and jaws go slack.
You know?
And then they kind of
start checking each other out.
And there's this tangible relaxation
that goes over the entire room,
as they realize,
this is just a scam I'm playing on myself.
And it is a scam, you know?
If a student managed to do everything
needed to get into this college,
to pass all of the entrance requirements,
maybe to get through that difficult first
year then, obviously, they have
the ability to do it because they did it.
And so when I make that speech,
as I say, it relaxes a lot of students.
And once you're familiar with
that phenomenon, what happens is,
imposters keep showing up.
I, in my office not a week goes
by that I don't see two or
three imposters coming into my office.
And as soon as they start talking about
the problems that they're having I,
okay, here's another imposter.
And I reach into the left middle drawer
of my desk in, in a file folder there.
I pull out a little copy of a little
column that I wrote on the imposter
phenomenon, and I say here check this out,
you might find it intriguing.
And so this imposter in my office
reads his or her biography.
And it's high drama, you know?
I get tears from male and
female imposters.
I get, you know, practically screaming.
I had one one woman student
accuse me of stealing her diary.
>> [LAUGH]
>> And so, it,
it's a really good thing for
teachers to know about, and it's a very,
very good thing for students to know
about, because we're all playing it.
>> It may surprise you to know that a lot
of us have that imposter feeling often.
And that's something that each of us has,
has struggled with in our whole adult
lives as well as when we were students.
And the, the power,
I think, is in naming it.
It's the imposter.
And once you realize that that's
what you're doing, then it,
it diffuses a lot of the power.
You can just remind yourself, okay,
I know how to do this, I can,
this may be something new, but I've met
challenges before, I'll meet this one.
I can do it.
And, and go ahead and, and push on.
And you'll find that,
as you get into whatever the task may be,
that you settle down and
you realize you really can do it.
And you have resources
if you have trouble.
>> Right.
So,
now let's turn to something
a little different.
What do you both do to avoid
procrastination when it
comes to something you'd
really rather not be doing?
Do you ever struggle with this?
It's hard to think that do these,.
>> Let me get,
let me get to you later on that.
>> Yeah.
[LAUGH].
>> We, when, when we figure it out,
we'll let you know.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Now, we definitely both struggle with
it, as I'm sure you,
you knew when you asked that question.
And we found some strategies for
each of us that work.
But it is still something we,
we struggle with.
I like to,
to try to schedule myself if I got a big task
schedule a small amount of time everyday
to work on it, to do just a little bit.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Not try to
do everything all at once but
to bite off a small, a small chunk.
I've also found it to be really helpful
where I keep a to-do list on my phone.
And I, if I break the task down into
smaller pieces, what's the very next thing
that I need to do that's manageable
then that makes it less overwhelming.
And I'm able to, to get going on it.
And once you get started,
it's easier to keep going.
>> Oh, absolutely.
>> the, this is one area where Rebecca and
I are exactly on the same page
because I use the same strategies.
There were two points in
the strategy that she mentioned,
which I'll just reiterate, one is breaking
it up into small pieces, you know?
If I think I've got to write the book, or
I've got to write the dissertation, or
I've got to write the 25-page proposal,
it's Mount Everest.
And it's very hard to get
myself to take that first step.
But if I say,
I've got to write the first two pages of
the introduction to this
thing that I can do.
That's not that formidable.
And so if I just break it
up into small pieces and
set easy targets for myself,
then I can keep marching.
And then the other
suggestion that she made,
which I would agree with is make
appointments with yourself.
So if if I work well in the morning,
I'm a morning person I,
I think well, I'm clear headed then,
then 10 o'clock to
10:30 every morning on my calendar,
I make an appointment with myself.
I'm going to work on that proposal,
for that half hour.
Then, I'll stop and
I'll go back to the rest of my life.
Next day, 10:00,
assuming I don't have other,
other obligations at 10:00,
I'll do another half hour on it.
And it's incredible how stuff gets done
when you can do things on a regular basis.
And the ones that you're
most reluctant to do,
that you're putting off because
I don't want to do that,
those are the ones that you got to
schedule appointments with yourself.
What a lot of people do is they work
on the block of time theory and
a time to work on the proposal now or
the term paper now.
But as soon as it's the weekend, as soon
as it's fall break, or anything like that,
that's when I'll really get it done.
And it doesn't work, among other things,
as soon as you get this block of time,
other things rush into fill it.
And also, it can be so
long since the last time you worked on it,
you forgot what you were doing.
And by the time you figure it out and
get your momentum back up,
the block of time may be over.
But the steady appointment to
just do the next chunk for
half an hour, it'll get done.
>> Some people find some form
of accountability is helpful.
A chart where they're
checking off the steps or
a friend who,
who will check in with them regularly.
How, how is it going on that project?
Are you making progress?
But those kinds of things
can be good strategies, too.
>> Absolutely.
Well, I'm
a big believer in the half hour chunk.
That time frame seems
to work really well for
me for something that I'm
having difficulty completing.
And I would like to thank you ever so
much for
your incredible responses that I think
people will find enormously helpful.
>> For great pleasure.
>> Thank you.