Khalid Azad has a passion for learning
concepts at a deep, intuitive level,
he writes at BetterExplained.com, which
serves millions of readers every year and
is used in dozens of university courses.
He's also authored a popular math book,
It's a pleasure to welcome Khalid.
Hi Khalid, thanks for joining us I,
I have to ask you first off, what got
you interested in this wonderful intuitive
approach to learning that you use?
>> You know it actually started with a
really frustrating math class I remember I
was in my freshman year at Princeton,
you know, I had always enjoyed math in
high school, middle school and I was in
my first class and I was just getting
destroyed. It was around the midterm, and
I wasn't happy, things weren't going well.
The subject that I'd always
liked just wasn't making sense
I remember the finals had come around and
I was cramming and cramming and
cramming, and suddenly some analogies
started coming to me about twists and
rotations and turns and that really
applied to the class, so I was able to
visualize the concepts instead of just
looking at the symbols and equations.
And because of that,
I didn't really need to memorize anymore,
I could just think through it, and I could
walk myself through my mental diagrams and
the equations kind of snapped into place,
and so after that I realized that
a lot of learning could become so much
more pleasant and more fun after we found
the right mental metaphors, diagrams,
and analogies Instead of trying to,
you know, bash our heads against the,
the raw definitions.
So from that I started trying to write and
share my, my insights that seemed to help me.
>> It sounds like we share the same
approach I'm, that's, that's the kind of
thing that I was trying to do,
too I finally sort of cottoned on to that.
So you can, can you talk a little bit more
about what approach you actually do use?
>> Sure just to keep things
straight in my head,
I have this little, mnemonic I use,
and I call it the ADEPT Method.
And basically what I'm looking for
in an explanation of something,
I try to find an analogy, a Diagram,
an Example, a Plain English description
and then a Technical Description.
And the, the general idea is actually kind
of a C.D.M, diffused thinking Is that you,
when you're first learning, you want to
start with the sort of fuzzy overview and
then gradually sharpen it up, until you
get to the technical details at the edge.
So you start with the analogy,
the diagram,
you get some examples, you have a plain,
plain English description, and
at the very end, that's when you
go to the technical description.
And you want to save that really
focused thinking, for me, for
last because that's when I already have
the framework in place to think about it.
>> Oh I like that, can you, can you share
a, a specific example of the ADEPT method?
>> Sure I think one of my favorite topics
is actually the the imaginary number,
so, most people myself included for a long
time, it is confusing, sound imaginary,
real safe you know, how can we use
in real life and after breaking it
down with the method, I was able to find
some metaphors that seemed to help me.
>> You just use an analogy,
then, to start with this?
>> Yeah, so, in this case,
imaginary numbers, a lot of the the time
we'll start the definition, the technical
definition, and that doesn't really make
things click one thing that helped me
was the analogy about a 90 degree turn.
So if you imagine that negative
numbers are sort of a full 180 so
you're going forward,
then you turn all the way 180 to backward.
A imaginary number is basically when you
start forward you actually just go up, so
instead of going all the way backward
you're actually just going up.
So, imagine maybe you're going east and
west negatives are sort of flipping
between east and west, but imaginary
number is the idea that hey maybe I
should take a 90 degree turn north.
So now you're going along and
woop you go north, and
suddenly you're in a different direction,
It's not just duress it's a new direction
it's a second dimension really and
that's kind of the key analogy behind it.
>> So in, in some sense then this can
actually become like a diagram or a map.
>> Exactly, this topic is really
easy to visualize because,
we already have the idea of second
dimensions and going different directions,
so in my head, I kind of imagine,
first a number going along,
and it gets a rotation,
which turns and then it turns again.
So I have this mental
diagram in my head.
And that actually leads right into
an example that well, you know,
a lot of kids wonder, well what
happens when you take four left turns?
Well if you keep turning, you'll face back
the same direction after four turns, and
with imaginary numbers
if you turn four times,
you'll face the positive numbers again.
And so the idea is that your
diagram can really, you know,
almost lead to an example that you can
figure out intuitively without having to
do a lot of math it kind of
worked through the results I got.
>> I used to do something very similar,
but
I had, what I had was a visual
with a toilet paper roll that was
unrolling because of scrolling across
the screen It was a lot of fun but,
but moving on so then you, actually
just use a plain English description.
>> yeah, so once you've,
wrapped your head around it
an analogy, a diagram, read about the example, start sharpening up what you've understood and
you want to describe it in your own words.
So rather than going right to the technical definitions,
lets think about what happens. I might say that we were moving in one direction and
we moved 90 degrees or we moved into a second dimension or there's kind of a different type
of number, there is one number that goes
this way and one type that goes this way.
In your head, you want to
get your own understanding,
put it in your own words and
eventually you sharpen it up and
can I think a lot of times we
try to understand things just by
someone else's words instead of
really internalizing it ourselves.
>> Well, I, I think this is the perfect
example of the real imaginative world
of mathematics and science and
engineering, I mean,
we imagine things in ways that people
don't ordinarily imagine and, and
I love how you're approaching this,
because it really brings this to life.
But, you, what you do then you
move next on to an actual technical
description of what you were describing?
>> Yeah, that's right, so the last step is
follow me to use the formal notation that
came up with my little analogy here,
its kind of like you have a song in
your head you might be humming it, doo ta
dit da doo, but, humming in your head but,
other people don't really know
what you're talking about.
You need to find the sheet music,
you know,
explain, you know the scale
that you're using, and
the notation, the timing, that way
somebody else can really have a handle for
the hymn, instead of this little
song that's going in your head.
So you want to take,
you know, the rough words and
kind of break them down
in a formal notation.
In the math world,
the notation is "i",
lower case "I" and that actually
represents, the imaginary dimension and
it's kind of like the number one but
in just that imaginary dimension, It is in
there, now we can start talking about
other ideas in a more technical sense.
So when I say, oh I want to face
forward and to take two terms, and
I'll be facing negative,
what that means is you start with one,
multiply by i, multiply by i again,
and you should be facing negative.
Which should be is negative, so
a mathematician might write one
times i times i is negative one.
Now you can simplify this you could say,
oh, one times i squared equals negative
one, and you can simplify it further
by just saying i squared equals -1.
And then the last step,
is if you really want to simplify it,
you just take the square
root of both sides, and
now you can say that i equal
the square root of -1.
Now, this makes sense to us hopefully
now because we've been able to
walk through it step by step, and turn our
kind of intuitive fuzzy description into
the really technical one, and it's
really painful to start with a technical
description I equals the square root of
negative one, and try to guess what that
could've meant, and I promise you
don't see all the steps ahead of time.
So I realized to myself I really needed
to start at the fuzzy level, and
work my way down to technical.
>> Yes I, I think that's the thing about
imaginary numbers people often don't
realize that they can dance,
that they can twist and
rotate and that's kind of what they
do It's quite beautiful actually,
do you have final learning tips for
our viewers?"
.
>> Yea, I think the biggest
tip that I might say is just,
have a sense for
yourself when something's not clicking.
And realize that it's probably just
because of a missing piece. So you know,
in the past they might have just
reread the same passage again and
again because it wasn't working, but
maybe if you want to defer a diagram,
Google Images or
maybe a talk or a slideshow, or
something that might have a different
metaphor that can help you.
I realize, you know,
with the ADEPT you know,
analogy diagram example plain-English
technical, I need all the parts It's kind
of a part of a complete breakfast I
need all the different pieces, and
then when I have them,
I know the idea is very quick in my mind.
So, if I'm working on something and
it's just a technical, maybe an example,
it's usually not enough for
me to really internalize it, so
I start searching for the elements there,
I didn't even know that there were other
pieces that I should be looking for so for
me, it's kind of a, checklist that helps
me kind of zone in on what to do with it.
>> Great well, thank you so much I know
our viewers will benefit greatly from
these ideas, which I myself have
found really valuable thanks again.