[BLANK_AUDIO]
We've mentioned it earlier, but it's worth
repeating.
Testing is itself an extraordinarily
powerful, learning experience.
This means that the effort you put
into test-taking, including the preliminary
mini test of
your recall and your ability to problem
solve during your preparation is of
fundamental importance.
If you compare how much you learn by
spending
one hour studying, versus one hour taking
a test on
that same material, you'll retain and
learn far more as
a result of the hour you spent taking a
test.
Testing, it seems, has a wonderful way of
concentrating the mind.
Virtually everything we've talked about in
this course
has been designed to help make the testing
process
seem straightforward and natural, simply
an extension of
the normal procedures you use to learn
the material.
So it's time now to cut directly to one of
the final features of this course.
A checklist, you can use to see whether
your preparation for test taking is on
target.
This checklist was developed by legendary
educator Richard Felder.
Although, it was originally developed for
engineers, it's actually suitable for many
disciplines.
As Doctor Felder says the answer to the
question, how should I prepare
for the test, is do whatever it takes to
be able to answer, yes.
Meaning, usually to most of the questions
on this list.
Did you make a serious effort to
understand the text?
Just hunting for relevent worked-out
examples doesn't count.
Did you work with classmates on homework
problems
or at least check your solutions with
others?
Did you attempt to outline every
homework problem solution before working
with classmates?
Did you participate actively in homework
group discussions contributing ideas and
asking questions?
Did you consult with the instructor or
teaching
assistants when you were having trouble
with something?
Did you understand all your homework
problem solutions when they were handed
in?
Did you ask in class for explanations of
homework problem solutions that weren't
clear to you?
If you had a study guide, did you
carefully go through it
before the test and convince yourself you
could do everything on it?
Did you attempt to outline lots of
problem solutions
quickly without spending time on the
Algebra in calculations?
Did you go over the study guide and
problems with class mates and quiz one
another?
If there was a review session before the
test, did
you attended and asked questions about
anything you weren't sure about?
And lastly, did you get a reasonable night's
sleep before the test?
If your answer is no, your answers to all
the preceding questions may not matter.
Taking a test is serious business.
Just as fighter pilots and doctors
go through checklists before takeoff and
surgery.
Going through your own test preparation
checklist
can vastly improve your chances of
success.
The answer to the question.
How should I prepare for the test becomes
clear once you've filled our Doctor
Felder's checklist.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning How to Learn.