Welcome to the last video of Learning How
To Learn.
If you're still listening to us, then
you've come all the way through the
course.
And may remember at the beginning, I said
that brains do not come with an
instruction manual.
So we have to write one ourselves.
And that was one of our goals.
In this final video, we want to tell
you how much we've enjoyed teaching and
learning.
We've learned from you as we hoped you've
learned from us.
The truth is you've always been in the
driver's seat when it comes to your own
learning.
But now that you have a better feeling for
what's under your neural hood,
you can use this to help you learn new
things all during your lifetime.
>> What we're hoping is that as the days
and months will pass you'll
continue to bring to mind some of the key
ideas you've learned in the course.
Approaches such as switching your mode of
thinking from focused to diffuse
can help reduce your frustration and allow
for more creative problem solving.
Strengthening your chunking can give you a
firmer grasp of the material.
Even seemingly tiny changes in your daily
approach to your work.
Using the pomodoro technique, for example,
can make a dramatic
long-term difference in your learning and
in your ultimate success.
>> Learning is so vitally important to our
future that most of us spend 12 to 16 of
our earliest years of our lives in school,
culminating in high school or college.
But the focus in formal education is on
the product of learning, not the process
of learning.
In this course, we've tried to give you a
better sense of the learning process.
Although this is our last video, we hope
it's not our last chance to influence you.
You have not truly learned something
unless you can teach it to others.
Teach those ideas to others and you will
find that
they will continue to resonate and deepen
in your own mind.
We hope you'll also have discovered how
powerful these ideas
can be at helping you broaden your
interest, passion, and expertise.
Many people believe that what they're
initially, sort of, naturally
good at is what they're supposed to be
doing in life.
But I myself am living proof that passions
can broaden, change, and grow.
The world is evolving and a broad tool kit
that allows you to learn effectively
in many different subject areas is one of
the most powerful assets you can have.
>> Best of luck in your life of learning.
>> Ditto that.