[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this video, I'm very pleased to
introduce you to Dr. Richard Felder and
Dr.
Rebecca Brent, two educators who have had
an enormous impact on the landscape of
education.
I first met Rich and Rebecca at the very
beginning of my teaching career.
I was lucky enough to attend a workshop
they taught on student centered learning.
That workshop changed the whole focus of
my teaching and
allowed me to understand learning in a
whole new, deeper way.
I think you'll find that your own
understanding of
learning will change as you listen to this
interview.
Rich Felder has written the best selling
book on introductory
chemical engineering in the country and
possibly in the world.
He's also won the Lifetime Achievement
Award from the
American Society of Engineering Education
for his enormously influential work.
But don't make the mistake of thinking
that
Dr. Felder's work is only useful for
engineers.
A big reason he's so influential is that
the approaches
he uses are applicable to virtually any
field of study.
It is actually Dr. Felder's enormously
gifted wife, Dr. Rebecca Brent, the
president of the education consulting
firm, Education Designs and long time
director of the NSF-sponsored SUCCEED
Coalition faculty development program, who
has
helped spearhead the broad
multidisciplinary impact
of the couples' work on education.
I think you'll find Dr. Felder and Dr.
Brent's work to
have as powerful an influence on you as
it's had on me.
So, you've written some extraordinarily
helpful advice
for students about how to prepare for
tests.
If you could sum that advice up in a
nutshell, what would you say?
>> Let me first say something about how
not to prepare for tests, which is what,
probably what about 90 plus percent of my
students do to prepare for tests.
One, they may read the book.
Generally, they ignore the book, but they
may read
the book like a novel, just going flipping
through
it, maybe they underline, which, as far as
I
can tell, is a singularly useless strategy
for doing anything.
And then when they've done that, maybe
they look through
the old homework solutions, and read
through them again like a
novel and then imagine that they've
studied, and that provides
them with no help at all in preparing for
the test.
First of all, the test is not going to be
just the homework again.
It's going to be new problems that they
have to solve.
So, if that's how not to do it, how do you
do it?
The only way that I've ever found that
works to prepare
for tests is and I'm talking about problem
solving tests now,
the kind that I give in engineering, is to
work problems,
to set problems up, not to work through
them in detail.
So I tell the students, you can start with
the
homework problems that you solve and then
solve it again.
Set up the solution without looking back
at the worked
out solution that was graded and see how
far you get.
If you can set it up so the only thing
that's
left to do is algebra or simple math, then
you're done.
Then go onto another problem.
Don't waste your time doing algebra and
arithmetic.
You're not learning anything from that,
and then maybe go to your book
and pick out another couple of problems,
and try to set those up.
And the more of that you do, the
better you're going to be at solving
problems, the more
likely you are to to be able to solve the
problems that show up on the tests.
And the other thing that I strongly advise
is work with other people.
Get into a study group.
Make it a serious study group and try to
make sure that at least somebody in
the study group is smarter than you are
and really knows how to solve the problem.
So that if you get stuck on something,
this person's likely to be
able to figure it out, and all of you go
marching along together.
And leave the beer and the snacks in the
refrigerator.
Just spend your time working through
problems, setting them up, making
sure you know how to solve it, going on
doing more problems.
And then, when you're either exhausted or
you've covered as much
as you need to cover, you can then hit the
refrigerator.
>> This is so much like what we've talked
about throughout this course as far as
simply putting, you, reading a book is not
putting it necessarily in your brain.
And to, to have to actively grasp the
material
and working with others sometimes is a
very good
way to help reinforce what you're learning
and also
fill in gaps in what you're trying to
learn about.
So, I think that's fabulous advice and I
have to say, thank you for that wonderful
check list.
>> You're welcome.
>> I think there's also some things you
can do when
you get in the test because sometimes it's
a high pressure situation.
You may feel a lot of anxiety.
And so, taking a moment when you get the
test, looking through the whole thing just
to get a sense of where you're going, pick
out the easy questions and start there.
And then if you get stuck somewhere, go on
to
something else that you, you feel
confident you can handle.
Keep moving, you know, don't stop.
Sometimes when we're anxious, we, we just
freeze.
And keep moving, keep working.
Even if you can't get everything, go for
partial credit.
>> Right.
>> Get some of it, put something down and
that will help you be more successful on
your test.
Also I've had students who really felt
rising anxiety if
they got to a question that they couldn't
answer right away.
If you find yourself really getting upset,
to just stop, take a
deep breath, pause for a moment and then
look back at it.
Just calming down a little bit can go a
long way.
>> Oh, it can.
Well, that's one of the things we've also
talked about
in the course, is breathing from the belly
to help
draw in and, and really do deep breathing,
that that's a very effective
technique to neuro-physiologically allow
yourself to calm down.
And another interesting thing and I think
for our viewers this shows a bit of
the difference in approach of different
top quality educators.
One thing we've talked about is, just
touch at
the very beginning when you're starting to
look through
a test, touch on and start working some of
the more difficult problems, just until
you get stuck.
So you, it takes willpower.
You have to pull yourself off quickly as
soon as you can detect that you're getting
stuck.
But that that actually gets your focused
attention on it, then pulls that attention
away.
And when you're working another, easier
problem, it allows you to,
to in the background, your diffuse mode
is, is working away.
And so, then you revisit that more
difficult problem, you've got a little
bit more going on intellectually because
you've had time to think about it.
If you wait for the, the and do the
hardest
problems later in the test, sometimes that
can create problems.
There's, so there's diff, different
approaches.
And I think, different folks, if they are
aware of the different kinds of approaches,
it gives them more tools that they can use
for their intellectual toolkits.
>> Exactly, I think that's always
important, to
look at all the advice, look at all the
suggestions, try things, give them enough
of a try
that you see how well they work for you.
So I think that's important for your
students [CROSSTALK] to always be, be
doing.
>> And I would extend that actually, the,
the advice you
just gave, I think is life advice, not
just for taking tests.
I mean, there's, there's this magical
phenomenon that I've experienced many
times in my life of I'm working on
something, a problem.
When I was a student, it might be a
problem on a homework assignment.
It could have been a problem on a test.
It could be a problem, it could have been
a problem
in my doctoral research or in a,
something I'm working on.
When I went into research as a faculty
member, but I'm struggling with something.
I can't make any headway on it.
My natural tendency is just to keep
grinding on
it and keep banging my head against that
concrete wall.
And it doesn't damage the wall at all.
>> [LAUGH]
>> It's not too good for my head.
And what I found is, when out of
desperation or just because I needed a
break
or whatever, I stopped grinding on it and
I went off and I did something else.
I took a walk, I took a nap, I went to
work on something else I was working on.
And then when I came around later, got
back
to work on the problem, the solution was
magically there.
And, you know, I, I, I tend to believe
what I've read in cognitive science about
all of the stuff going on underneath the
conscious part that I'm aware of.
And somewhere in that part of my brain is
somebody or
something that's a lot smarter than
whatever I think of as me.
And once I've gotten started on the
problem exactly as you've
just described, and then I get away from
it and it's like
I'm turning it over to that part of my
brain which
is smarter and it somehow solves the
problem when I come back.
There's the solution, like magic.
>> Yes, that's, that's the idea, is
basically when you
purposefully pull your attention off or
allow your attention to drift
off, that actually opens access to the
resting, the neural resting
states that you need to be able to solve
the problem.
And just alluding to some of the same life
issues, sometimes my husband and
I will be, we'll be thinking about a
problem that we have to solve.
For example, how do we schedule
interviews, how do we and,
and we'll say, you know, we don't have to
solve this tonight.
And sure enough, within another day or
two, the answers will come to us.
>> My mother used to call that give your
subconscious an assignment.
So, I often think about that.
>> Your mother was very, very smart.
[BLANK_AUDIO]