[BLANK_AUDIO]
Well let me ask you this, now.
When you, yourself are faced with a new
concept or you're trying to figure
out something brand new and it's
difficult, what advice would you have
in general for learners to be able to, to
grapple with
and assimilate these new ideas or solve a
new area that they're first facing?
>> Well, just like with the test question
that we talked about, I think
there are a lot of different ways to
approach a difficult task.
And in fact as we were thinking about
talking about this
issue Rich and I realized that we, we
approach things differently.
My I'm a rather big picture person.
More of a global kind of learner.
And so, often when I'm looking at some
difficult material
I'll take time if I have some thing a
chapter, or
some sort of text, I'll look through it, I'll
just skim through.
I read a little at the end, I will pick up
a piece here and there and then begin to
dig in a
little bit deeper, but I do better when I
sort of have
a general sense of what it is I'm supposed
to be learning.
I might skip to the back and look at what
kind
of problems am I supposed to be able to
solve with this.
And so when you're working in disciplines
where problem solving is an important
part that can be a way to get into it, to
begin to make sense of it.
>> And the way that I differ from Rebecca
is I'm a strongly sequential learner.
And so I take the first step, then the
next step, then the next step.
But, again, I never learned anything
passively.
Anything non-trivial.
If it's just a simple fact of definition
of a
term I can read it and memorize it, but if
it's
really conceptually difficult, whether
a part of a problem-solving procedure,
a derivation that I'm trying to work
through or anything else.
The only way I learn anything is by doing
it.
So, I'll read this and then I'll try to
explain it to myself.
or, what I, when I've learned things best
of
anything at all is when I've had to teach.
And I think practically every teacher will
tell you the same thing.
You know, I thought I knew this stuff.
I got As in all those courses back in
college.
But it wasn't until I had to explain it to
these students that I was teaching that
I found out that I really didn't
understand
it at the level that I thought I did.
And so I try to find examples.
I try to find clear ways of explaining
difficult concepts.
And in the course of doing that that's
when the real understanding came,
and so this is another strong argument,
among other things, for working in groups.
If you can if you're working with other
people
and together you're trying to figure
something out and
you get a certain point and then you try
to explain it to the others you're
reinforcing your understanding.
And they may or not, may not understand it
after your
finished figuring out how to explain it,
but boy do you.
And so those two pieces of advice.
I learn by doing things, by trying them.
If it's a mathematical method or procedure
or
something in physics or in engineering,
then I try
to work out the solution myself without
looking
back at the book, the text, whatever it
is.
And when I can do it by myself without
referring back, then, obviously, I know
how to do it.
And then to really reinforce that
understanding, explaining it to someone
else.
Put those two things together, and well,
at least that's how I learned it.
>> I think using your resources too.
Whatever those resources may be.
You've got text, you've got things online,
you
have people who really understand that
difficult thing
that you're trying to learn and, and so
make, not being afraid to just go out
ask questions work with all the resources
you
have to try to find what's going to work
for you to make it clear, to make you more
confident figure out what you're doing.
>> Oh, absolutely.
>> Playing, playing off of that, one of my
biggest
problems as a professor is getting
students to ask questions.
>> [LAUGH].
>> They don't want to do it.
And it's not that, well some of us,
sometimes
they're so confused that they don't know
what to ask.
But much more often it's a matter of fear.
You know if I ask a question in class, it
could be seen by my classmates as a dumb
question.
And we as instructors can make all of the
pretty
speeches we want about how there are no
dumb questions.
All questions are good because they tea-,
forget that.
>> [SOUND].
>> Right?
I, the students are not buying that, and
besides, to be perfectly honest, there are
dumb questions.
>> [LAUGH]
>> And we've all heard them.
And so the student is reasoning, if I open
my mouth to ask a question, I
could be perceived as dumb by my
colleagues, my classmates, my professor.
If I keep my mouth shut I'm risking
nothing and so they don't
ask, and I also can't persuade most of them
to come to my office.
I have office hours every week, in which I
tell the students, I'm there for you.
I promise I will be there.
I will be welcoming of any questions that
you ask.
I'll find out where you're getting stuck
and you won't
leave my office until you have the answer
to that question.
Maybe for the same fear they don't want to
come.
And so, they're not taking advantage of
the resources that Rebecca was referring
to.
And if a student can be persuaded to
overcome that fear
and just ask either in class or in the
office in five
minutes they can get things cleared up
that they could spend
three hours at home banging their heads
against and not getting clear.
Let me go back to a couple of points I
made before.
The best way to get the illusion of
competence
when you don't really understand something
is to listen
to a lecture or to read a text, like
a novel, or to read over old homework
solutions.
And imagine that you understand them.
Because you don't.
The best way to get over the illusion of
competence is to do it.
Solve the problem, again, without looking
back at the old solution.
Work out the derivation one step at a
time without looking back at the textbook
or your
lecture notes or whatever it is, and when
you can do it by yourself without any
reference.
When you can reproduce that solution
entirely by yourself then it's not
an illusion of competence, clearly you can
do it because you did it,
but it's not until you do it, actually
unaided, that you can
rest that, okay, I'm ready for the test or
whatever it may be.
>> This can also be a good time for
working with your peers.
Taking turns, explaining, a work, perhaps
a worked out example in the text.
Explaining it step by step to each other.
When you start trying to verbalize it then
you begin to see, wait a minute, I, I,
I thought I knew how they made that step,
but when I try to explain it, I, I don't.
So what, what's going on?
Let's look at it.
So I think that working with other people
can really help you in that way too.
So one of the things that you can do to
make sure
you are thinking about all the different
aspects of the
subject that, that you're trying to
understand and it's to set it up.
Look at a complex system that might be
used in a problem in your text.
And then just think about, what are about all
the things
that the teacher might ask me to do with
this system.
And in working through that you begin to
think about
all of the elements that need to be in
place.
So that's a great way to study for a test.
It's also a great way to sort of get past
that illusion
of competence because as you're looking at
it and as you're working through
the example and what you think you might
be asked you'll uncover
some things that maybe you don't know as
well as you thought you did.