[BLANK_AUDIO]
This week we are going to wrap up a slew
of important ideas, and techniques that
will help round out and
enhance your ability to learn well, using
metaphors and analogies,
to work profitable with teammates, and not
undercut your own strengths.
And finally to perform well on tests.
One important thought though, before we
launch into this week's videos.
Learning doesn't progress logically, so
that each day just
adds an additional neat package to your
knowledge shelf.
Sometimes you hit a wall in constructing
your understanding.
Things that made sense before can suddenly
seem confusing.
This type of knowledge collapse seems to
occur when your
mind is restructuring its understanding,
building a more solid foundation.
In the case of language learners, they
experience occasional
periods when the foreign language suddenly
seems completely incomprehensible.
Remember it takes time to assimilate new
knowledge.
You'll inevitably go through some periods
when you seem
to take and exasperating step backwards, in
your understanding.
This is a natural phenomenon, that means
that
your mind is wrestling deeply with the
material.
You'll find that when you emerge from
these periods of
temporary frustration, your knowledge base
will take a surprising leap forward.
I'm Barbara Oakley, thanks for learning
how to learn.