Now that you've gotten some insight into
how your brain works, we
can give you some final useful tricks that
can empower your test taking.
The classic way students are taught to
approach
tests is to tackle the easiest problems
first.
This is based on the idea that by the time
you finish
the relatively simple problems, you'll be
confident in handling the more difficult.
This approach works for some people,
mostly
because, well, anything works for some
people.
Unfortunately, however, for many people
it's counterproductive.
Tough problems often need lots of time,
meaning you'd
want to start on them first thing on the
test.
Difficult problems can also scream for the
creative powers of the diffuse mode.
But to access the diffuse mode, you need
to not
be focusing on what you so badly want to
solve.
What to do?
Easy problems first, or hard?
The answer is to start with the hard
problems but quickly jump to the easy
ones.
Here's what I mean.
When the test is first handed out to you,
first take
a quick look to get a sense of what it
involves.
You should do this in any case.
Then, when you start working the problems,
start
first with what appears to be the hardest
problem.
But steel yourself to pull away within the
first minute or two, if you get
stuck or you get a sense that you might
not be on the right track.
This does something exceptionally helpful.
Starting hard loads the first most
difficult problem
in mind and then switches attention away
from it.
Both these activities are what allow the
diffuse mode to begin its work.
If your initial work on the first hard
problem
has unsettled you, turn next to an easy
problem.
And complete or do as much as you can.
Then move, next, to another difficult
looking problem
and try to make a bit of progress.
Again, change to something easier as soon
as
you feel yourself getting bogged down or
stuck.
When you return to the more difficult
problems, you'll often be pleased that the
next step or steps in the problem will
seem to be more obvious to you.
You may not be able to get all the way to
the end immediately, but at
least you can get further before you
switch
to something else of which you can make
progress.
In some sense, with this approach to test
taking, you're being a little like an
efficient chef.
While you're waiting for a steak to fry,
you can swiftly slice the
tomato garnish and turn to season the soup
and then stir the sizzling onions.
The hard start jump to easy technique may
make more efficient use of your brain by
allowing different parts of the brain to
work simultaneously on different thoughts.
Using the hard start jump to easy
technique on tests guarantees that
you will have at least a little work done
on every problem.
It's also a valuable technique for helping
you avoid Einstellung, getting stuck on the
wrong approach - because you have a chance
to look at the problem from differing
perspectives.
All of this is particularly important if
your instructor gives you partial credit.
The only trick with this approach is that
you must have the self discipline to
pull yourself off a problem once you find
yourself stuck for a minute or two.
For most students it's easy, for others it
takes discipline and willpower.
This may be why test takers sometimes find
that the solution
pops to mind right as they walk out the
door.
When they give up, their attention
switched, allowing the diffuse mode the
tiny
bit of traction it needed to go to work
and return the solution.
Too late of course.
Sometimes, people are concerned that
starting a problem and then
pulling away from it might cause confusion
on an examination.
This doesn't seem to be a problem for most
people.
After all, chefs learn to bring various
facets of a dinner together.
But if you still have worries about
whether this strategy
might work for you, try it first on
homework problems.
Also keep in mind that if you haven't
prepared
well for a test, then all bets are off.
Just take what simple points you can.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning how to learn.
[BLANK_AUDIO]