Doctor Keith Devlin is a very big
guy in the world of math education,
not to mention the world of math research.
I'm introducing you to him here because
I love how he thinks about learning in
the world of mathematics, and
how his ideas about learning relate to
learning in all sorts of topics
way outside of mathematics.
Among many other duties, Keith is
a Co-Founder and Executive Director of
Stanford's Human Sciences and
Technologies Advanced Research Institute,
a co-founder and president of
an educational technology company,
BrainQuake, that creates
mathematical learning video games.
He's also a World Economic Forum fellow,
a fellow of the American Association for
the Advancement of Science, and a fellow
of the American Mathematical Society.
Last, but definitely not least, he is
The Math Guy on National Public Radio.
Welcome, Dr. Devlin.
Thanks for being with us here today,
Doctor Devlin.
Let's just dive right in.
What's the biggest tip you can
share with our viewers about how to
most effectively approach a math
problem that they might be stuck on?
Well the first thing,
of course, is don't panic.
That's a famous Douglas Adams motto from
The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy, and
it holds just as much for mathematics as
it did, for, for The Hitchhiker's guide.
You have to begin by understanding
what the problem's about.
What are you trying to do?
What do you want to achieve?
And, what information do you have?
You must have, you,
I mean you've really gotta avoid the thing
that actually teachers try to impress on
you of trying to see if you can match
it to some template and to act quickly.
One of the worst things that I think
happens in the school system is people
come away thinking that solving math problems is
something that has to be done at speed.
It absolutely is not.
So you have to sit back,
take a deep breath,
begin by understanding the problem.
If the problem involves numbers, put in
a few simple numbers, threes and fours and
just play with it to get a sense of it.
If it's a geometric problem,
do some little diagrams or
you, I often end up writing simple little
graph diagrams with dots and lines
connecting them, just some things to give
me a sense of what that problem's about.
At that point, you can ask yourself,
do I know any techniques that look as
though they would work with this problem?
If they do, and you're in luck,
the problem's solved.
Actually that's usually very
unsatisfying because you've just
applied someone else's thinking.
Mathematics gets interesting when your,
you have to force yourself to find a new,
a new method or some new approach.
So, lets assume that none of
the techniques you know work.
The next thing is can I
adapt an existing technique.
Well, maybe you can, maybe you can't.
If you can that usually leaves you
with a nice feeling because
you've done something yourself.
The really challenging ones are the ones
where it gets actually exciting and
fun is where you, you it becomes clear at
least you think that nothing you know is
going to help you with that.
At that point, what you do is you, you,
you basically, you bash away at it
several times which just naive approaches
almost certainly they won't work.
You just try this and you try that.
You, you come up with ideas based
on what the problem's asking you
to do because solving
a problem is a journey.
You begin with the information you've got,
either the information your given with the
problem or information you already know.
You may have to add some extra
information, you may do a Google search,
find some extra information about it.
At that point, the journey takes place and
you have to get to the goal and
solve the problem.
If none of the methods you try for
the first oh, half hour, maybe depending
on the problem it could be half hour,
couple of hours,
sometimes it's a day or a few weeks.
But if nothing happens, then the best
thing to do is walk away from the problem,
go and do something else.
In my case, for
most of my career I was a long distance
runner, if I really came up against it.
I would put on my running gear, whatever
the weather and I'd go out for a three or
four hour run, and when I came back,
A, I felt good, I felt relaxed, and
quite often on the course of ride or
that, that, that run or
when I got back, the problem seemed
different and I had some new ideas.
As I got older my knees gave away
from 25 years of heavy duty running,
these days I ride a bicycle.
But I go on my bike and I go for
a three or four hour bike ride and
I come back, and first of all I can
approach the problem with a fresh eye and
secondly in some cases what seemed to be
an impassible problem just melted away.
I look at it and think oh, gee, that was
obvious, why didn't I see it before?
Well, I don't quite think that because I
know that the feeling you have when you
solve a problem is always oh, duh,
why didn't I think of that before.
And if that doesn't work
you start the cycle again.
You bash your way at it again, make no
progress and then you go, you go and
have another bike ride or a swim or
whatever it is you like to do.
A nice long walk.
But it's important to keep oscillating
between bashing away at it and
then backing off and doing something
else to let the brain do it's own thing.
I think that was one of
the hardest things for
me to realize was how
important it is to back away.
That sometimes, especially when it's
something difficult, it's as important to
be able to focus on it as it is to
be able to back away from it and
then come back later with a fresh
perspective and a fresh mind.
Okay, I, it, it, for,
for difficult problems,
I have never, ever solved a difficult
problem sitting at a desk or
even sitting in my chair,
thinking about the problem.
I've never done that, and
I'm not sure it's possible to do that.
Because if you think about it,
if a problem/solution requires something
new applying all of your conscious
thinking by definition can't solve it
because you're looking for something new.
The weird thing about the brain
is when you've done that
preparation of bashing away without
success and you go and do something else
I'll mention physical activity because I'm
a sort of a physical, active guy, although
the biggest result in my PhD was actually
when I was getting out of the bath.
I'd taken a long bath, you don't have
to sort of exert lots of energy,
you have to do something different.
Having a bath is a famous one among
mathematicians for solving problems.
But somehow weird stuff happens inside the
brain when you're doing something else and
what three hours ago seemed like
an impossible problem just melts away and
everything just falls into place.
The brain sorts it out when
it's left alone to do it.
And that's exactly the kinds of ideas that
we're talking about in in our course.
It is important to do that initial work.
It's no good just going out for
a bike ride.
You've got to have gone through that
process of really coming up against it and
seeing everything that doesn't work, because
that seems to set up the mind in
order to do this mysterious stuff it does
when you're engaged in something else,
when your conscious mind is
engaged in something else.
Absolutely.
It, that's so important.
Well one thing that you've
described is that in
higher mathematics there should be a lot
less doing and a lot more thinking.
Can you tell our viewers what
you mean by that and how,
how does that relate to areas of
learning that are outside mathematics?
Yeah, and, and this is really
where you've got unlearn lots of
the things that you're taught at school.
And actually you're taught,
teachers do that for very good reasons,
because of the way we, especially in
the United States and parts of Europe,
the way we subject people to endless
test taking in, with timed tests.
The, the way to get through the school
system is to learn to act fast
under pressure of time, and
that's the last thing you can
do when it comes to mathematics.
You've really got to
let it take its course.
It's not,
I mean people have different speeds, I,
I've worked with some
very fast mathematicians.
The young math professor from Stanford
who won a Fields Medal recently.
She has gone on record as saying,
his teachers at school thought she
wasn't good at mathematics
because she was so slow.
Well, she may be slow, but she now has a,
the equivalent of a Nobel prize in
mathematics and, and
congratulations to her for doing that.
You really have to let it take its time.
It's a slow process.
You've got to remember that mathematics
is relatively recent, you know 2 or
3,000 years, so your bringing
what's essentially a stone age
brain to a domain that is
a couple thousand years old,
In fact, most mathematics
is only a few decades old.
So, how can you take this brain,
that evolved to survive in the wilds and
then more recently to survive
in social environments,
how can you take that brain and apply it to
solve this abstract problem in mathematics?
Well, the answer's we don't
really know how we do that.
What we do know is that if
you familiarize yourself with
the problem to such an extent that,
that problem is like a member of your
family, then the act of solving that math
problem is actually not unlike solving
a difficult problem you have at home.
You know, we're very good at
solving social problems and
problems about our environment,
because evolution set us up for that.
So, somehow we have to
figure out how to let
that brain solve that abstract
problem in mathematics.
And the act of getting
inside the problem and
thinking about it for
a long period of time, so that it's so
familiar, then the natural circuits in
the brain, that, that, that serve us
well all of the time actually come
into play for a math problem.
Now it, there's no proof of that,
but that's certainly my own
experience of what goes on.
Yes.
Well, all I can say is,
three cheers for slow thinking.
And I love the idea of
thinking about math and, and
a difficult problem as being something
that's a member of your family.
Yeah, it's a, you know, it.
Math in many ways mathematics
problems are not, it's not,
they're not fundamentally different
from other problems except in one
respect they're about
totally abstract things.
So, someone solving their math
problems has an initial problem
that someone doesn't have if they're
solving their problem in real life or
a coaching problem in,
in sort of football.
Or, or, or, in a, you know, most of, I
used to spend a lot of time rock climbing,
and rock climbing is,
is partly physically, but
it's also a lot of problem solving
because you're having to look for
these moves, you're having to
move your body in the right way.
So there's an awful lot of problem
solving that we do all of the time,
and that's what the brain evolved to do.
And in the case of mathematics however,
the world in which you're solving those
problems isn't one we are familiar with.
You initially have to create that,
that world inside of you, and
this, I think, is why it's essential
to knock away at the problem for,
10-15 minutes a day, two days before
you let the brain do it's own thing.
My guess and my perception of what's
going on, is that, that process is
making my mind familiar with that demand,
with that problem to such an extent that,
that problem is just like
a problem I'd have with my family.
or, or, or my work place or whatever.
I've got all of this apparatus for solving
real world problems and social problems,
and once that math problem is inside my
mind, it's another problem just like that.
So, solving the math problem
usually isn't the hard part,
the hard part is getting that problem
familiar inside your mind, and the only
way to do that is just keep living in
the problem, get inside the problem.
Really live inside that problem for
ten minutes, half an hour,
maybe even a few days.
In the case of Andrew Wiles,
solving Fermat's Last Theorem a few
years ago, it took him seven years to
really get inside that problem to
the point where he could see the solution.
Well, part of what you do when you're
spending a lot of time with a problem is
you're in some sense reifying and
growing the neural structures,
that are related to what
you're trying to think about.
And one of the things that Dr. Sejnowski
and I emphasize, quite strongly in our
course is how exercise helps
actually build neural structures.
It, it allows you to learn better,
it allows you to remember better.
So, how, how does exercise play a role
in your own ability to do mathematics?
That's that's a good one.
But it certainly is the case for me.
In fact, when I was a PhD student and
my closest colleague was a, was a,
was a, a mathematician from
from the United States,
came over to England when I
was a student back in Bristol.
And he was a rock climber,
in fact I learned to rock climb with him.
And we used to go on these three or
four hour rock climbs.
And we would almost certainly,
by the time we got to the,
to the top of the climb we'd done some
mathematics, because you do a climb and
you get to a ledge and you're,
you're tied up and then you chat for
a while as you sort of
belayed onto the rock face.
And we'd talk about mathematics and
then we'd forget the mathematics and
we go and
do the physical stuff of climbing.
And when you're climbing, as when, as when
you're bicycling very fast your mind is
totally focused on that physical activity,
that's your your entire world is physical.
So, you're focused on the climbing or
you're focused on riding your bike, but
stuff is going on in
the background in your mind.
It's working on those things
that you talked about.
And we'd finish your pitch,
we'd get ourselves back on belay we
talk about the problem and
we've made progress on the problem.
So as a graduate student I
discovered this method of thinking,
doing, thinking,
doing was incredibly powerful.
I can make conjectures and,
and sort of self reflect as to why
the physical activity is important.
I mean aspects clearly are.
You're focusing on that activity.
It's very refreshing you know,
we tend to think these days that
the mind is separate from the body.
I don't buy that.
It certainly isn't the case for me.
I find that if my body's tired,
my mind is tired and
vice versa, they stimulate each other.
So, you know, the mind did evolve
to help the body survive, and
I think it's a mistake to try
to think of those as separate.
If you nurture the body the mind follows.
I, you know, this, this goes back to
the ideas of having physical education in
schools and so forth.
This is hardly original but
I think we need to take it seriously,
I've never ever,
well I have solved problems in the bath.
That's a, that's a,
a somewhat more relaxing case.
But even in the bath it's a really,
you know, it's a, it's a,
it's an artificial environment
in which you are relaxed.
You're in water, you're doing things,
you're fresh, you're freeing up the mind.
The mind is absolutely not
thinking about that problem.
It's doing other things in my
case definitely, the bath,
the bath example not withstanding,
physical activity plays a big role.
Exactly why I don't know,
but I do know it works.
[LAUGH] Well there is actually
good research evidence.
They're uncovering the,
the biophysiological mechanisms
by which it does take an effect.
but, I, I have to ask,
with everything that you do.
Do you ever catch yourself, it's hard to
believe but do you ever procrastinate, and
if you do,
what do you do to get yourself out of it?
Yeah well first of all I do do many things
you know, I've got my own educational
technology company, I do lots of biking I,
I run an institute at Stanford, I do my
teaching, I do, I'm actually on Twitter
a lot, I do a whole bunch of things.
You might think I'm a multitasker.
I absolutely do not multitask, not least
because I know from the research that's
been done here at Stanford,
a lot of it by my late colleague Cliff Nass,
that shows that, a) human beings
cannot multitask, and b) the more you
think you're good at multitasking,
the worse you are at doing it, so.
I absolutely don't try to use this
serial processor to multitask.
What I do is, I serial task.
I will work exclusively flat out for
periods of time.
Now they may only be ten minutes,
they may be half an hour, or they may be.
I mean, recently I had to develop
a whole set of 75 puzzles, a new set of
puzzles for, for my educational video
game that we launched last fall.
We wanted to bring out
a different version.
I worked nonstop on that for 4 days.
I didn't do anything else other than eat,
sleep, and bicycle ride.
And my entire focus, everything else went
to one side, was to get that thing done,
and four days later I had the 75 puzzles
worked and tested and everything.
And then I moved to something else.
So what I do is I work very intensely and
very focused for periods of time.
I mean, it's amazing that, that,
that friends and family are still by me,
because this is very focused and
it excludes everything else.
You know, I must be really difficult
to live with at those times, but
everything gets excluded.
I focus on it and then I,
there comes an end.
Now, either because I finished the job or
I just get tired and want to switch and,
and I'm really getting, getting
frustrated with it, then I'll switch and
do something else.
And what I've learned to do
very efficiently is switch from
one to the other.
It doesn't take me more than a few minutes
at most to switch from one to the other.
The procrastination comes from recognizing
that I need to make that switch.
I'll keep going and keep going and
think, I want to this other thing,
I want to do this other thing.
And I do find myself doing
lots of other little things.
I'll go and start and
read my Twitter feed and things for
a while before making the switch.
So, the one moment where I will
procrastinate is starting something new,
for obvious reasons.
You've been in the groove,
you've been making process and
it's slowed down and
you've got to get in another groove.
And I know that that takes will power and
effort, and like everybody else I do have
a procrastination streak, but the only
time it affects me is making that switch.
Once I've done it, I'm away in that domain
until I've either solved that issue or
done it or completed it or
got tired of it and need a break.
And that I found works extremely well.
That's, that's actually something
that we talk about in this course.
Is just that idea of you don't need
to use willpower all the time,
you just need to put it one little place,
wherever you need,
where you're getting that cue, that's
where you need to be applying will power,
and that seems to be exactly what you do.
And it's true that I'm fortunate to
have been able to carve out a career for
myself where most of the time,
I'm doing stuff I really want to do.
So even though I may not want to write
that blog post, I know in the back
of my mind that the moment I get into it
and have written the first sentences,
writing that blog post will be the most
important and most wonderful and
rewarding thing in the world
until it's finished.
But then I have to sort of stop that and
do something else.
And that's when these hiatus moments when,
when, I procrastinate.
It's the, the, the switching gears
to something else that's, that's,
that I find.
I won't say I find it difficult,
because I've been doing it all my life,
but you do need willpower to do that.
At least I find I need
willpower to do that.
And if I'm not careful,
it will just fritter away with
social media or whatever.
I feel the same way in
how I handle things.
One thing I, I like to do is I
think of it, my life as like this
enormous funnel where there's all these
things that are demanding to be done, but
then only one thing can go
through the funnel at a time.
And so you just gotta give it up and
realize one thing is all
you can be focusing on.
And if you have that approach it makes it
a little easier to realize that
you just can't do everything.
You just do as much as you reasonably can.
Yeah, I mean, one thing I do do is when I
actually just upgraded my computer system.
to a new Macintosh.
The first thing I did is went into
the into the system controls and
switched off every single alert.
I don't want visual alerts, I don't
want noise alerts, I don't want know if
an email has come, I don't want
to know if something's going on.
I literally switch off all the alerts
because I don't want things pushed to me.
I want to go and find out things when I
need them, because the last thing I want,
if I'm in the middle of working on
an article say, is to have some little,
little beep going off to tell
me some email has arrived.
I don't want to know then
because that's a distraction.
I want to be in the world of
writing that article because if you
take this human brain, and you put it
into a problem, into a domain, and
you set it free, it loves what it's doing,
and it doesn't want to give up,
and it sure doesn't want to be distracted.
And so, I don't distract it.
I just let it do what it does.
Well, I, I,
I thank you so much, Doctor Devlin for
sharing your wisdom with us, here today.
It's just been a great
pleasure talking to with you,
and I know our viewers will really, really
learn a lot from what you had to say.
Okay, the pleasure's been all mine,
absolutely.
Thanks, so much.