In this video, we're going to delve deeper
into memory.
Another key to memorization is to
create meaningful groups that simplify the
material.
Let's say you wanted to remember four
plants that help ward off vampires.
Garlic, rose, hawthorn and mustard.
The first letters abbreviate to GRHM, so
all you need to
do to remember is use the image of a
graham cracker.
It's much easier to remember numbers by
associating them with memorable events.
The year 1965 might be when one of your
relatives was born for example.
Or you can associate numbers with a
numerical system you're familiar with.
For example, 11.0 seconds is a good
running time for the 100 meter dash.
Or 75 might be the number of stitches on
a knitting needle for the ski hats you like
to make.
Personally, I like to associate numbers
with the feelings of,
when was I was or will be at a given age.
The number 18 is an easy one.
That's the age when I went out into the
world.
By age 104 I hope to be an old, but happy
great grandma.
Many disciplines use memorable sentences
to help students memorize concepts.
The first letter of each word in the
sentence is also the
first letter of each word in a list that
needs to be memorized.
Medicine, for example, is laden with
memorable mnemonics.
Among the cleaner of which are: some
lovers try
positions that they can't handle to
memorize the names
of the carpal bones of the hand, and old
people from Texas eat spiders for the
cranial bones.
Time after time, these kinds of memory
tricks prove helpful.
If you're memorizing something commonly
used, see whether someone has come
up with a particularly memorable memory
trick by searching it out online.
Otherwise try coming up with your own.
The memory palace technique is a
particularly powerful
way of grouping things you want to
remember.
It involves calling to mind a familiar
place.
Like the layout of your house, and using
it as a sort of a
visual notepad where you can deposit the
concept images that you want to remember.
All you have to do is call to mind the
place you're familiar with.
Your home, your route to school, or your
favorite
restaurant and voila in the blink of an
imaginative eye.
This becomes the memory palace that you'll
use as your notepad.
The memory palace technique is useful for
remembering unrelated items, such as a
grocery list.
Milk, bread, eggs.
To use the technique, you might imagine a
gigantic bottle of milk just inside your
front door.
The bread plopped on the couch and a
cracked
egg dribbling off the edge of the coffee
table.
In other words, you'd imagine yourself
walking through a place you
know well, coupled with shockingly
memorable
images of what you want to remember.
If you're studying Finance, Sociology,
Chemistry or what have you, and
you have lists to remember, you could use
this same approach.
The first time you do this, it will be
slow.
It takes a bit of time to conjure up a
solid mental image.
But the more you do it, the quicker it
becomes.
One study showed that a person using the
Memory Palace technique could remember
more than 95% of a 40 to 50 item list after only one or two practice mental
walks, where the items were placed on the
grounds of the local university.
In using the mind this way, memorization
can become an outstanding exercise in
creativity that simultaneously build
neural hooks for even more creativity.
Purists might sniff that using
oddball memorization gimmicks isn't really
learning.
But researchers show that students who use
this kind of tricks outperform does who
don't.
In addition, imaging research
on
how people become experts, shows that such
memory tools speed up the acquisition of
both chunks and big picture templates.
Helping transform novices to semi experts
much
more quickly, even in a matter of weeks.
Memory tricks allow people to expand their
working
memory with easy access to long term
memory.
What's more, the memory process itself
becomes an exercise in creativity.
The more you memorize using these
innovative techniques, the more creative
you become.
This is because you're building these
wild,
unexpected possibilities for future
connections early on.
Even as you're first internalizing the
ideas, the more you practice this type
of memory muscle so to speak, the more
easily you'll be able to remember.
Where at first it may take 15 minutes to
build
an evocative image for an equation and
embed it say,
in the kitchen sink of your memory palace,
it can
later take only minutes or seconds to
perform a similar task.
You'll also realize that as you begin to
internalize key aspects of the material.
Taking a little time to commit the most
important points to memory.
You come to understand it much more
deeply.
The formulas will mean far more to you,
than they
would if you simply looked them up in a
book.
And you'll be able to sling those
formulas around
much more proficiently on tests and in
real world applications.
You may say, well, you're just not
that creative, an equation or theory could
hardly
have its own grandiose motivations or
persnickeity emotional
needs to help you understand and remember
it.
But always remember, your childlike
creativity is still there inside you.
You just need to reach out to it.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning how to learn.
[BLANK_AUDIO]