[BLANK_AUDIO]
Just imagine backing out of a driveway for
the first time ever in your life.
For some of you, that might seem like a
pretty exciting proposition.
The first time you might do this you would
be in hyper alert.
The deluge of information coming at you
would make the job seem almost impossibly
difficult.
But, once you've chunked how to back up
down your
driveway, all you have to do is think,
let's go.
And, off you go.
Your brain goes into this sort of zombie
mode, where it is only semi
aware of a few key factors, instead of
being overwhelmed by all the data.
It's the same idea with riding a bicycle.
At first, it's really hard, later it's
easy.
Neuro-scientifically speaking, chunking is
related to habit.
Habit is an energy saver for us.
It allows us to free our mind for other
types of activities.
You go into this habitual zombie mode far
more often than you might think.
That's the point of habit, you don't have
to think in
a focused manner about what your doing
while you're performing the habit.
It saves energy.
Habits can be good and bad.
They can be brief, like absently brushing
back your hair.
Or they can be long, for example when you
take a walk,
or watch television for a few hours after
you get home from work.
You can think of habits as having four
parts.
The first is the cue.
This is the trigger that launches you into
zombie mode.
The cue may be something as simple as
seeing the first item in your to do list.
Time to start next week's homework.
Or seeing a text message from a friend.
Time to stop work.
A cue by itself is neither helpful or
harmful, it's the routine.
What we do in reaction to that cue, that's
what matters.
Number 2, the routine.
This is your zombie mode.
The routine habitual response your brain
is used
to falling into when it receives the cue.
Zombie responses can be useful, harmless,
or sometimes harmful.
Number 3, the reward.
Every habit develops and continues because
it rewards us.
It gives us an immediate little feeling of
pleasure.
Procrastination's an easy habit to develop
because the reward, moving your
mind's focus to something more pleasant,
happens so quickly and easily.
But good habits can also be rewarded.
Finding ways to reward good study habits
is important for escaping procrastination.
Number 4, the belief.
Habits have power because of your belief
in them.
For example, you might feel you'll never
be able to change
your habits of putting off your studies
until late in the day.
To change a habit, you'll need to change
your underlying belief.
I'm Barbara Oakley, thanks for learning
how to learn.