[BLANK_AUDIO]
Learning for most people involves a
complex balancing of many different tasks.
A good way for you to keep perspective
about what you're trying to learn and
accomplish,
is to once a week write a brief weekly
list of key tasks in a planner journal.
Then each day on another page of your
planner journal, write a
list of the tasks that you can reasonably
work on or accomplish.
Try to write this daily task list the
evening before.
Why the evening before?
Research has shown that this helps your
subconscious to grapple with the
tasks on the list so you can figure out
how to accomplish them.
Writing the list before you go to sleep,
enlists your zombies,
to help you accomplish the items on the
list the next day.
If you don't write your tasks down on a
list, they lurk at the edge
of the four or so slots of your
working memory, taking up valuable mental
real estate.
But once you make a task list, it frees
working memory for problem solving.
So let's look at one of my daily task
lists.
As you can see here, there are only six
items.
Some are process oriented.
For example, I have a paper due to a
journal in several months.
So, I spend a little focus time on most
days working towards completing it.
A few items are product oriented.
But that is only because they are doable
within a limited period of time.
Note my reminders.
I wanted to keep my focus on each item
when I'm working on it.
And I want to have fun.
I did catch myself getting sidetracked,
because I forgot to shut down my email.
To get myself back into gear, I set a 22
minute Pomodoro challenge, using a timer
on my computer desktop.
Why 22 minutes?
Well, why not?
I, I don't have to do the same thing each
time.
And notice, too, that by moving to
Pomodoro mode, I've switched to a process
orientation.
None of the items on my list is too big,
because I've got other things going on in
my day.
Meetings to go to, a lecture to give.
Sometimes I sprinkle a few tasks that
involve physical
motion on my list, even if it's just
cleaning something.
Which, I'll admit, isn't ordinarily one of
my favorite things to do.
Somehow because I'm using them as diffuse
mode breaks, I often look forward to them.
Mixing other tasks up with your learning
seems to make everything
more enjoyable and keeps you from
prolonged and unhealthy bouts of sitting.
Over time, as I've gained more experience,
I've gotten much better
at gauging how long it takes to do any
given task.
You'll find yourself improving quickly as
you become more realistic
about what you can reasonably do in any
given time.
Make notes in your planner journal about
what works and what doesn't.
Notice my goal finish time for the day, 5
p.m.
Doesn't seem quite right, does it?
But it is right, and it's one of
the most important components of your
daily planner journal.
Planning your quitting time is as
important as planning your working time.
Generally, I aim to quit at 5 p.m.,
although when I'm learning something new,
it can sometimes be a pleasure to
look at it again after I've taken an
evening break, just before I
go to sleep, and occasionally, there's a
major project that I'm wrapping up,
like say, this MOOC that has me running
into a bit of overtime.
You might think, well, yeah, you know, but
you're a
professor who's shall we say, past your
youthful study days.
Of course an early quitting time is fine
for you.
However, one of my most admired study
experts, Cal Newport, used the 5 p.m.,
quitting time through most of his student
career.
He ended up getting his PhD from MIT.
In other words, this method, implausible
though it may seem for some, can
work for undergraduate and graduate
students in rigorous academic programs.
Time after time, those who are committed
to maintaining healthy leisure time along
with their hard work, outperform those who
doggedly pursue an endless treadmill.
Of course, your life may not lend itself
to such a schedule with breaks and leisure
time.
You may be running on fumes with two jobs
and too many classes.
But however your life is going, try to
squeeze a little break time in.
One more thing.
As writing coach Daphne Graygrant
recommends to her
writing clients, eat your frogs first in
the morning.
Try to work on a most important and most
disliked task first.
At least just one Pomodoro, as soon as you
wake up.
This is incredibly effective.
Do you need to sometimes make changes in
your plans because of unforeseen events?
Of course, but remember the law of
serendipity.
Lady Luck favors the one who tries.
Planning well is part of trying.
Keep your eye on your learning goal, and
try not to get too unsettled by
occasional roadblocks.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning how to learn.
[BLANK_AUDIO]