[BLANK_AUDIO]
Learning to use your memory in a
more disciplined yet creative manner helps
you
learn to focus your attention, even as you
create wild diffuse connections that build
stronger memories.
Here are the key ideas about memory we've
covered.
In this course, we discussed two main
memory
systems involved in your ability to chunk
concepts.
The first is long term memory, which is
like a storage warehouse.
You need to practice and repeat in order
to help store items
in long term memory so you can retrieve
them more easily.
Practicing and repeating, all in one day,
is a bad idea.
You want to extend your practice to
several days.
This is why tackling procrastination is
important.
It helps you build better memories.
Because you start earlier.
The second, is working memory, which is
like a poor blackboard that quickly fades.
You can only hold about four items in your
working memory.
When you master a technique or concept in
some sense, it compacts the ideas so
they can occupy less space in your working
memory when you do bring them to mind.
This frees your mental thinking space so
that
it can more easily grapple with other
ideas.
We have outstanding visual and spatial
memory systems.
If you tap into those systems, it will
help improve your memory.
To begin tapping into your visual memory
system, try making a
very memorable visual image representing
one key item you want to remember.
Beyond merely seeing, try to feel, to hear
and even to smell something you're trying
to remember.
The funnier and more evocative the image
is, the better.
As always, repetition over several days is
really helpful.
Another key to memorization is to
create meaningful groups that simplify the
material.
Try associating numbers with years or with
systems you're familiar with like running
times.
Many disciplines use memorable sentences.
The memory palace technique, placing
memorable images in a
scene that's familiar to you, allows you
to dip into
the strength of your visual memory system,
providing a
particularly powerful way of grouping
things you want to remember.
By making meaningful groups and
abbreviations,
you can simplify and chunk what
you're trying to learn so you can more
easily store it in memory.
And by memorizing material you understand,
you
can internalize the material in a profound
way.
You're reinforcing the mental library you
need
to become a genuine master of the
material.
Happy memories. I'm Barbara Oakley. Thanks
for learning how to learn.