[BLANK_AUDIO]
This week we're going to be talking about
two seemingly different ideas.
Procrastination and memory.
But the two topics are intimately related.
Why?
Because building solid chunks of long term
memory, chunks that
are easily accessible by your short term
memory, takes time.
It's not the kind of thing you want to be
putting off until the last minute.
You already have one good tool for
procrastination.
The pomodoro.
That powerful 25 minute concentrated
period of energized focus.
This week we're going to fill you in with
more
information about how procrastination
happens and simple ways to tackle it.
And this is key.
Ways that don't take much will power, then
we'll move on to talking about some of the
best ways to access your brain's most
powerful long-term memory systems.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning how to learn.