[BLANK_AUDIO]
Learning well often involves bit by bit,
day by day building of solid neural
scaffolds.
Rather like a weight lifter builds muscle
with day to day exercise.
This is why tackling procrastination is so
incredibly important.
You want to keep up with your learning and
avoid last minute cramming.
So with that, here's an overview of the
key aspects of tackling procrastination.
Keep a planner journal so you can easily
track when
you reach your goals and observe what does
and doesn't work.
Commit yourself to certain routines and
tasks each day.
Write your planned tasks out the night
before so your brain
has time to dwell on your goals and help
ensure success.
Arrange your work into a series of small
challenges.
Always make sure you, and your zombies,
get lots of rewards.
Take a few minutes to savor the feelings
of happiness and
triumph, which also gives your brain a
chance to temporarily change modes.
Deliberately delay rewards until you've
finished a task.
Watch for procrastination cues.
Try putting yourself in new surroundings
with few procrastination
cues, such as the quiet section of a
library.
Gain trust in your new system.
You want to work hard during times of
focused concentration and also to trust
your system enough
so that when it comes time to relax,
you actually relax without feelings of
guilt or worry.
Have back up plans for when you still
procrastinate.
No ones perfect after all.
Eat your frogs first every day.
Happy experimenting.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning, how to learn.