[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this video, we're going to get into the
specifics of harnessing your zombie powers
of habit to help you avoid procrastination
while minimizing your use of willpower.
You don't want to do a full scale change
of old habits.
You just want to override parts of them
and develop a few new ones.
The trick to overriding a habit is to
look to change your reaction to a cue.
The only place you need to apply willpower
is to change your reaction to the cue.
To understand that, it helps to go back
through the four
components of habit and re-analyze them
from the perspective of procrastination.
The first one is the cue.
Recognize what launches you in to your
zombie procrastination mode.
Cues usually fall into one of the four
following categories.
Location, time, how you feel and
reactions.
Either to other people or to something
that just happened.
Do you look something up on the web and
then find yourself web surfing?
Does a text message disturb your studying
taking you 10 minutes to get back
into the flow of things even when you try
to keep yourself on task?
The issue with procrastination is that
because it's an
automatic habit, you're often unaware that
you've begun to procrastinate.
You can prevent the most damaging cues by shutting off your cell phone or
keeping yourself away from the internet
and
other distractions for brief periods of
time.
As when you're doing a pomodoro.
Number two, the routine.
Let's say then instead of doing your
studies
you often divert your attention to
something less painful.
Your brain wants to automatically go into
this routine when you've gotten your cue.
So this, is the reaction clue where you
must.
Actively focus on rewiring your old habit.
The key to rewiring is to have a plan.
Developing a new ritual can be helpful.
Some students make it a habit to leave
their phone in their
car when they head in for class which
removes a potent distraction.
Many students discovered the value of
settling into a
quiet spot in the library or closer to
home,
the productive effects of simply sitting in
a favorite
chair at the proper time with all Internet
access disconnected.
Your plan may not work perfectly at first,
but just keep at it.
Adjust the plan if necessary, and savor
those victories when your plan works.
Don't try to change everything at once. The
Pomodoro Technique
can be especially helpful in shifting your
reaction to the cues.
Number three is the reward.
This can sometimes require a little bit of
investigation.
Why are you procrastinating?
Can you substitute an emotional payoff,
maybe a feeling of pride
for accomplishing something, even if it's
small, a sense of satisfaction?
Can you win a small internal bet or a
contest about something you've turned into
a personal game or allow yourself to
indulge in a latte or read a
favorite web site, provide yourself,
maybe, with
an evening of mindless television or web
surfing without guilt, and will you give
yourself a bigger reward for a bigger
achievement?
Maybe movie tickets or a sweater or an
utterly frivolous purchase.
Remember that habits are powerful because
they create neurological cravings.
It helps to add a new reward if you want
to overcome your previous cravings.
Only once your brain starts expecting that
reward will the important
rewiring take place that will allow you to
create new habits.
Many people find that setting a reward at
a specific time.
For example, breaking for lunch with a
friend at the
deli at noon or stopping the main task at
5 p.m.,
gives a solid, mini deadline that can help
spur work.
Don't feel bad if you find you have
trouble getting into a flow state at
first.
I sometimes find it takes a few days of
drudgery, through
a few cycles of the pomodoro technique
before flow begins to unfold.
And I find myself starting to enjoy
work on a new
topic.
Also remember that the better you get
at something, the more enjoyable it can
become.
Number four is the belief.
The most important part of changing your
procrastination
habit is the belief that you can do it.
You may find that when the going gets
stressful.
You long to fall back into old, more
comfortable habits.
Belief that your new system works is what
can get you through.
Part of what can underpin is to develop a
new community.
Hang out with classmates, or virtually
hang out with MOOC-mates, who
may have that can-do philosophy that you
too want to develop.
Developing and encouraging culture with
like-minded friends can help
us remember the values that, in moments of
weakness.
We tend to forget.
I'm Barbara Oakley, thanks for learning
how to learn.
[BLANK_AUDIO]