Arsenic is incredibly toxic.
For centuries until modern methods of
detection were discovered
murderers found it to be a very popular
substance.
So you can imagine the shock at the 48th
meeting of the German Association of Arts
and Sciences.
In 1875 when two men sat in the front of
the audience and downed more than double
a deadly dose of arsenic. The next day the
men were back at the conference smiling
and healthy.
How is it possible to take something so
bad for you and stay alive, and even
look healthy, despite the damage being
done at a microscopic level to your body?
The answer has an uncanny relationship
To procrastination that's what we're going
to
be talking about in the next few videos.
You've already learned one handy tool
to help you with procrastination the
pomedoral
that 25 minute period of uninterrupted
focus followed by a bit of relaxation.
This week we're going to learn more.
Understanding a little about the cognitive
psychology of procrastination, just like
understanding the chemistry of poison, can
help us develop healthy preventatives.
In these videos, I'm going to teach
you the lazy person's approach to tackling
procrastination.
This means you'll be learning about your
inner zombies.
The routine, habitual responses your brain
falls into as a result of specific cues.
These zombie responses are often focused
on making the here and now better.
As you'll see you can trick some of these
zombies
into helping you fend off procrastination
when you need to.
Not all procrastination is bad.
Even if you're pretty good already in
handling procrastination you'll learn some
helpful insights here tha can allow you to
better prioritize your learning.
The reason that learning to avoid
procrastination is so important
is that good learning is a bit by bit
activity.
You want to avoid cramming which doesn't
build solid neural structures.
By putting the same amount of time into
your learning
but spacing that learning out by starting
earlier you'll learn better.
First things first.
Unlike procrastination which is easy to
fall into, willpower is hard to come by.
It uses a lot of neural resources.
You shouldn't waste willpower on fending
off procrastination except when absolutely
necessary.
Best of all as you'll see you don't need
to.
If you'll remember we procrastinate about
things
that make us a little bit uncomfortable.
You think about something you don't
particularly
like and the pain centers of your brain
light up so you shift and narrow
your focus of attention to something more
enjoyable.
This causes you to feel better.
At least temporarily but sadly the long
term effects of habitual avoidance can be
nasty.
When you put off your studies it can
become even more painful to think about
studying it.
You can choke on tests because you haven't
laid the firm neural foundations you need.
To feel comfortable with the material.
Procrastination can be a single
monumentally important keystone bad habit,
a habit in other words that influences
many important areas of your life.
If you improve your abilities in this area
many other positive changes will gradually
begin to unfold.
Procrastination shares features with
addiction.
It offers temporary excitement and relief
from sometimes boring reality.
It's easy to fool yourself for example
into thinking
that the best use of any given moment is.
Surfing the web for information instead of
actually
reading the textbook or doing the assigned
problems.
You start to tell yourself stories.
For example you might tell yourself that
organic chemistry requires spacial
reasoning, your weakness, so of course
you're doing very poorly at it.
You devise irrational excuses that sound
superficially reasonable like if I
study too far ahead of the test I'll
forget the material.
If you're troubled by procrastination you
may even start
telling yourself that procrastination is
an innate unchangeable characteristic.
After all if procrastination were easily
fixable wouldn't you have fixed it by now?
The higher you go in your studies however
the
more important it is to take control of
procrastination.
Habits that worked in earlier years can
turn around and bite you.
What I'll show you in these next few
videos is how you can become.
The master of your habit.
You should be making the decisions not
your well-meaning but unthinking zombies,
your habits.
As you'll see the strategies for dealing
with procrastination are simple.
It's just that sometimes they aren't
intuitively obvious.
So let's return to that story that began
this video.
The arsenic eaters started with tiny doses
of arsenic.
In tiny doses, arsenic doesn't seem
harmful.
You can even build up an immunity to its
effects.
This can allow you to take larger doses
and look
healthy, even as the poison is slowly
increasing your risk of
cancer and ravaging your organs.
In a similar way procrastinators put off
just that one little thing.
They do it again and again gradually
growing used to it.
They can even look healthy but the long
term effects? Not so good.
I'm Barbara Oakley. Thanks for learning how
to learn.