Hi everyone, I'm Caroline.
I live in Atlanta, Georgia, USA.
And I grew up in Miami, Florida
where I was always good at reading.
I liked art, philosophy, stuff like that.
I was the girl in elementary school who
got in trouble for
reading behind the desk in math class.
[LAUGH] And a little bit later in
high school I got in trouble for
skipping math altogether
to go the beach instead.
[LAUGH] I have two older sisters
one of them became a doctor,
the other became a lawyer.
So I had a lot to live, live up to.
And my parents thought their youngest
child who was kind of a free spirit,
math and science hating kid
would end up with a degree
in creative poetry,
cartoon drawing, or something.
But to everyone's surprise,
I chose mechanical engineering
as my major at Auburn.
And that was kind of weird
because it combined all of
the subjects that I was worst at.
And people always, now, and
in school, they always ask me
why I would choose that major?
And Dr. Oakley promotes this
idea of broadening your
passions instead of just following them,
which I think is just an incredible idea.
And it perfectly describes what I
was feeling going into this field.
I knew that I was always going to
have a passion for English and
art and
all the things that I've always loved.
But now, I have these new passions for
engines and power tools and
coding, and
stuff I never even knew that I liked.
[LAUGH] And that's really cool.
It's cool to find interest
that you never knew you had.
School was really hard for me.
A lot of my peers had
worked in auto shops and
they were certified machinists and
all sorts of technical brains.
And, so it was really hard for
me to keep up because I had never
even changed my own oil before.
[LAUGH] But I worked my butt off for
four years and I got through.
And it really paid off,
because upon graduation I got this amazing
job with Lockheed Martin Aeronautics.
And I work with some of the most
advanced technology and
coolest military aircraft
in the whole world.
And I feel like I'm valued at my job
just as much for
my problem solving skills and
my engineering skills that I learned
in school, as my creativity and
my communication skills,
my writing skills, my people skills.
And it's good to feel
proud of yourself for
stuff that you were naturally born with.
But it's also really cool to feel
proud of yourself for working
really hard to learn how to do something
that you weren't actually good at.
So that's kind of why
I went into my field.
So thanks guys.
Good luck.