Barb Oakley here,
I'm going to do a quick walk-through for
you so you see how to
handle all the videos and everything you
are going to be accessing, on our website.
So when you first land, you'll probably
find something like this on the homepage.
This welcome to learning how to learn.
Now, if you look at
the left navigational bar,
you'll see video lectures readings and
so forth.
So, first thing you might want to do
is just go to the video lectures,
that's a key part of the course.
Now I have special powers, so I get to
access everything right from the very
beginning, so you're seeing
actually right here you're seeing.
Most of the lectures for Week One, Week
Two, Week Three, Week Four and so forth.
So, now one thing you can do, is you can,
once you've completed a week,
see how you can press this arrow and
press it back, so
you can diminish the size of any
particular week, if you want to.
And then, one thing I want you to do is
I want you to look over to the right.
And you'll see these wonderful
little images, which related to, for
example, Power Point's.
This is a Powerpoint, for the first video.
This image right here,
takes you to the discussion forums.
So, you can see when you click on it,
you just go right to the discussion forum.
Here are the, captions for the videos
right here and then you can download
the videos by clicking, right here and
and then it just shows up as.
As it's busy downloading.
So, you can week by week
the videos will come available.
And you'll be able to see them.
And so, there, you're kind of
getting a little preview here.
And then, what you can do is you
can go over to the reading section.
And you can see that we've got lots of,
good stuff for you.
Here's a little bit of background about A
Mind for Numbers, the book for the course.
And, of course,
you don't have to buy the book.
But it's nice to have in,
incase you want to look into or
sort of ingrain some of
the ideas more deeply.
Here's one of the keep
aspects of the book.
And also of the course.
Which are some guidelines
about how to study and
how not to study because
you can fool yourself.
And then for
each week we also have a note for
readings that might be worthwhile for you.
All of these readings are optional and,
but they,
they just give you some nice insights
either into more popular articles or
heavy duty articles if you want
to take a look and see what.
What you might have an interest in.
Now the quizzes, as you go over
here you'll see the quizzes.
Here's the quiz for
week one is right up there, and
you can just attempt quiz one
whenever you think you're ready.
And week by week each quiz
will come available, and
then of course at the end
of the last week you'll.
You'll have access to the final.
Now here are the peer or
the loop mate assessments.
So if you go and just take a look,
there's, remember there's two assessments.
One is Assessment 1 and
the second is Assessment 2.
And you can see all the details
about these two assessments and
down at the bottom of the page.
Are the actual assignments
themselves that you can go off to.
So then, there's a little bit here in the
About section, basics about the course.
So here's a little bit of
an introduction again, and
it pretty much repeats what's
on the introductory page.
And then a little bit more about
assessments and certificates.
And of course, the verified certificate
is a very nice way to go if you want to.
Really be,
show people that you've actually
learned the material in the course.
Here's a nice listing of
the actual course objectives.
And some frequently asked questions
that relate to the course.
And here's a little bit
of information about us.
There's Dr. Sejnowski right here.
And.
Then me.
And then we've got a number of learning
experts that we've interviewed for
the course.
So you'll see them as
bonus material interviews.
Here's our wonderful teaching assistants.
And you can see we've got
a great number of them.
And then a little bit about
the temporal dynamics learning center.
And finally our development team who have
worked very hard to help make
this course come to reality.
And there's a little bit here about you.
Right now,
I'm when I'm making this video, there's,
it's before the class
has actually started so.
Pretty soon, this is going to
be populated with a lot of
different folks from all around the world.
And then, it, within a week or
so, we'll be giving you a survey.
And then we'll let you know what
the results of that survey are, and
they'll show up here.
Now, an important part of the,
the course, is the discussion forums.
So, the discussion forums,
they're right here.
Don't be shy.
And you can see, as I showed you earlier,
each of the video lectures actually
has a connection over to here.
So you can go directly here from the video
lectures, or you can come independently.
And then also, you can go from the quizzes
to study groups and hanging out together.
There's all sorts of different.
Aspects that you can meet people, talk
to them and get some insights from them.
Finally, there are some worthwhile
pages for you to go explore,
if you want to learn a little further;
just people I've found interesting and
worthwhile and
different websites and so forth.
So I think you'll find
this possibly of interest.
And that is almost all.
There's a little bit about meetups here.
You can go in and
learn about meetups and form a meetup.
And that's pretty much it for the course.
So that's your pocket
walk-through of our course.