Welcome to Learning How to Learn.
Your brain has amazing abilities, but it
didn't come with an instruction manual.
Perhaps the greatest gif that our brains
give
us is the ability to learn new things
everyday.
On my way here, I thought about the
journey that will take us to
the last day of the course and how much we
will learn along the way.
Our goal is to give you a better
understanding of
how we learn, so that your brain becomes a
better learner.
These insights are based on solid
research from neuroscience, from cognitive
psychology,
and also from dozens of leading
instructors and practitioners in
difficult-to-learn subjects.
Whether you're a novice or an expert, you
will find great new ways
to improve your skills and techniques for
learning, especially related to math and
science.
>> This course is meant to help you
reframe how you
think about learning, to help reduce
your frustration and increase your
understanding.
We approach things a little differently.
You're not expected to have an in-depth
background in any particular subject.
Instead, you're expected to take these
ideas
and apply them to whatever subject you're
trying
to learn or improve in, to help you
learn more deeply, effectively, and with
less frustration.
You'll hear experts from a variety of
different disciplines
talking about their best tips for learning
more effectively.
You can benefit from these ideas whether
you are struggling in high
school or soaring through math and science
at graduate levels at a university.
>> I'm a co-director of a science and
learning center that
is sponsored by the National Science
Foundation, based here in La Jolla.
In recent years, we've made great strides
from
research, in discovering how to learn most
effectively.
Finding a way to simply and effectively
share these ideas with you,
has been a big undertaking, but we feel
it's well worth doing.
You'll see that many of these ideas,
although simple, are incredibly powerful.
And along the way, we'll also learn a lot
in the process of teaching you.
>> You'll see how you can fool
yourself about whether you actually know
the material.
You'll discover new ways to hold your
focus and
embed the material more deeply and
powerfully in your mind.
And you'll learn to condense key ideas
you're learning about, so you can grasp
them
more easily, master the simple, practical
approaches outlined
here, including simple tips to help
prevent procrastination.
And you'll be able to learn more
effectively and with less frustration.
This course is meant to enrich both your
learning and your life.
You'll able to get what you want from this
material.
So, welcome to the course, and happy
learning.