When I look back on my childhood or I
remember some words from Spanish or from
Russian, Здравствуйте, or
I bring to mind one of Maxwell's
equations, I'm drawing
on portions of my brain involved in long
term memory.
But what I'm trying to hold a few ideas in
mind to connect them together
so I can understand a concept or solve a
problem, I'm using my working memory.
Obviously, sometimes I'll bring something
from my long term memory
into my working memory, so I can think
about it.
So the two types of memory are related.
There are lots of different ways to slice
our understanding a memory, but for this
course on
learning, we're going to talk about only
these two
major memory systems, working memory and
long term memory.
Working memory is the part of memory that
has to
do with what you're immediately and
consciously processing in your mind.
Your working memory is centered out of the
prefrontal cortex, although as we'll see
later, there
are also connections to other parts of
your
brain ,so you can access long term
memories.
Researchers used to think that our working
memory
could hold around seven items or chunks,
but
now it's widely believed that the working
memory
is holds only about four chunks of
information.
We tend to automatically group memory
items in to chunks so
it seems our working memory is bigger than
it actually is.
Although your working memory is like a
blackboard, it's not a very good
blackboard.
You often need to keep repeating what you
are trying
to work with so it's stays in your working
memory.
For example, you'll sometimes repeat a
phone number to
yourself until you have a chance to write
it down.
Repetition's needed so that your
metabolic vampires, that
is, natural dissipating processes, don't
suck those memories away.
You may find yourself shutting yours eyes
to keep any other items
from intruding into the limited slots of
your working memory as you concentrate.
So we know that short term memory
is something like an inefficient mental
blackboard.
The other form of memory, long term
memory, is like a storage warehouse.
And just like a warehouse, it's
distributed over a big area.
Different kinds of long term memories are
stored in different regions of the brain.
Research has shown when you first try to
put a
short term memory in long term memory, you
need to revisit
it at least a few times to increase the
chances that
you'll be able to find later when you
might need it.
The long term memory storage warehouse is
immense.
It's got room for billions of items.
In fact, there can be so many items they
can bury each other, so it can be difficult
for you to find the information you need
unless
you practice and repeat at least a few
times.
Long term memory is important because it's
where you store fundamental
concepts and techniques that are often
involved in whatever you're learning
about.
When you encounter something new, you
often
use your working memory to handle it.
If you want to move that information into
your
long term memory, it often takes time and
practice.
To help with this process, use a technique
called spaced repetition.
This technique involves repeating what
you're trying to retain, but
what you want to do is space this
repetition out.
Repeating a new vocabulary word or a
problem
solving technique, for example, over a
number of days.
Extending your practice over several days
does make a difference.
Research has shown that if you try to glue
things
into your memory by repeating something 20
times in one evening,
for example, it won't stick nearly as well
as if
you practice it the same number of times
over several days.
This is like building the brick wall we
saw earlier.
If you don't leave time for the mortar to
dry, that is, time for
the synoptic connections to form and
strengthen,
you won't have a very good structure.
And talk about lasting structure, look at
this part of the Acropolis here.
Thanks for learning about learning.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
[BLANK_AUDIO]