Everybody has some issues with
procrastination.
Because if you're working on something, it
means
you're not working, on a lot of other
things.
But some people have more issues with
procrastination than others.
In this video, we're going to give you a
little insight into procrastination.
Why it arises, and a powerful little tool
to help you address it.
When you look at something that you really
rather not do, it
seems that you activate the areas of your
brain associated with pain.
Your brain, naturally enough, looks for a
way to stop
that negative stimulation by switching
your attention to something else.
But here's the trick.
Researchers discovered that not long after
people might start
actually working out what they didn't
like, that neurodiscomfort disappeared.
So it seems what happens when you
procrastinate, is something like this.
First, you observe, and get a cue about
something that causes a tiny bit of
unease.
You don't like it, so to make the
sensation go
away you turn your attention from whatever
caused that unease.
You turn toward something more pleasant.
The result, you feel happier, temporarily.
We're going to talk more about
procrastination later on.
But in the mean, time I'm going to let you
in on a handy little mental tool.
This tool is called, the Pomodoro.
It was invented by Francesco Cirillo, in
the early 1980's.
Pomodoro is Italian for tomato.
The timer you use often looks like a
tomato and really,
a timer is all there is to this elegant
little technique.
All you need to do, is set a timer
to 25 minutes, turn off all interruptions,
and then focus.
That's it!
Most anybody can focus for 25 minutes.
The only last important thing is to give
yourself a little reward when you're done.
A few minutes of web surfing, a cup of
coffee, or a bite of chocolate, even
just stretching or chatting mindlessly,
allowing your brain
to enjoyably change its focus for a while.
You'll find that using the Pomodoro
technique is very effective.
It's a little like doing an intense 25
minute workout at a mental gym.
Followed by some mental relaxation.
Give it a try.
Next, we're going to see how one very shy
ten year old, changed her brain.