You might be surprised to learn that just
plain being awake creates toxic products
in your brain.
How does the brain get rid of these
poisons?
Turns out that when you sleep, your brain
cells shrink.
This causes an increase in the space
between your brain cells.
It's like unblocking a stream.
Fluid can flow past these cells and wash
the toxins out.
So sleep, which can sometimes seem like
such a waste of
time, is actually your brain's way of
keeping itself clean and healthy.
So, let's get right to a critical idea.
Taking a test without getting enough sleep
means you're operating with
a brain that's got little metabolic toxins
floating around in it.
Poisons that make it so you can't think
very clearly.
It's kind of like trying to drive a car
that's got sugar in its gas tank.
Doesn't work too well.
In fact, getting too little sleep doesn't
just
make you do worse on tests, too little
sleep, over too long of a time, can
also be associated with all sorts of nasty
conditions.
Including headaches, depression, heart
disease,
diabetes, and just plain dying earlier.
But sleep does more than just allow your
brain to wash away toxins.
It's actually important part of the memory
and learning process.
It's seems that during sleep your brain
tidies
up ideas and concepts your thinking about
and learning.
It erases the less important parts of
memories and
simultaneously strengthens areas that you
need or want to remember.
During sleep your brain also rehearses
some
of the tougher parts of whatever you're
trying to learn, going over and over
neural patterns to deepen and strengthen
them.
Sleep has also been shown to make a
remarkable difference in your ability
to figure out difficult problems and to
understand what you're trying to learn.
It's as if the complete deactivation of
the conscious you in the
pre-frontal cortex at the forefront of
your brain helps other areas of
your brain start talking more easily to
one another, allowing them to
put together the neural solution to your
learning task while you're sleeping.
Of course, you must also plant the seed
for
your diffuse mode by first doing focused
mode work.
If you're going over what you're learning
right before you take a nap or
going to sleep for the evening you have an
increased chance of dreaming about it.
If you go even further and set it in mind
that you want to dream about the material,
it seems to improve your chances of
dreaming about it still further.
Dreaming about what you're studying can
substantially enhance your ability to
understand.
It somehow consolidates your memories into
easier to grasp chunks.
And now time for a little sleep.