Although living brains are pretty complex,
this week we've
used metaphor and analogy and zombies to
help simplify matters.
In essence, people have two fundamentally
different modes of thinking that,
for the purpose of this course, we've
labeled focused and diffuse.
We used a simple pinball analogy to
help us understand the differences between
the modes.
The focused mode has tight spacing for the
rubber bumpers
which seems to, in some sense, help keep
your thoughts concentrated.
The diffuse mode, on the other hand, has
more widely
spaced bumpers that allow for more broad
ranging ways of thinking.
The focused mode is centered more in the
prefrontal cortex, and
it often seems to involve thinking about
things you're somewhat familiar with.
For example, if you're familiar with
multiplication and you're trying to solve
a
multiplication problem or you're trying to
find a word that rhymes with another word.
You're probably stepping along the
somewhat
familiar pathways of the focused mode.
But if you're trying to solve or figure
out something new, it
often cries out for the more broad ranging
perspectives of the diffuse mode.
This mode, as it turns out, is
representative of the brain's many neural
resting states.
Creative thinkers throughout history,
whatever their discipline, have found ways
to access the diffuse mode, often more
directly and quickly.
But we all access this mode quite
naturally when we do things like go
for a walk or take a shower or even just
drift off to sleep.
When we find ourselves stuck on a problem,
or even if
we're unsure of a situation in the course
of living our daily
life, it's often a good idea, once you've
focused directly on the
situation, to let things settle back, and
take a bit more time.
That way, more neural processing can take
place,
often below conscious awareness in the
diffuse mode.
The thing is, it often takes time for
neural processing to take place, and time
as well to build the new neural structures
that allow us to learn something new.
This is why tackling procrastination is so
very important.
The easiest way to tackle procrastination
is to use the Pomodoro Technique.
That brief 25 minute stretch of focused
concentration, followed by a bit of mental
relaxation.
It's through practice and repetition that
we can help enhance and
strengthen the neural structures we're
building as we're learning something new.
Practice and repetition is particularly
important for more abstract topics.
Memory, of course, is an important aspect
of learning.
There are four slots in our working
memory.
Things can fall out of those slots unless
we keep repeating them to hold them in
mind.
In that sense, working memory is like a
not very good blackboard.
Long term memory, on the other hand, is
like a storage warehouse.
If you practiced and repeated something
well enough to get
it into long term memory, you can usually
call it
up later if you need it, although you may
need
an occasional bit of repetition to freshen
the memory up.
It's never a good idea to cram your
learning
by repeating things many times all in one
day.
Because that's like trying to build muscle
by lifting weights all in one day.
There's no time for solid structures to
grow.
We've also learned of the importance of
sleep in
washing away the toxins that develop
during our day's activities.
You want to avoid taking tests or doing
anything difficult with little sleep
the night before, because it's like trying
to think with poison on the brain.
And just as importantly, exercise is
surprisingly valuable in
helping improve both our memory and our
ability to learn.
We've had a lot of fun while learning this
week, I'll
bet you'll find next week's material to be
even more exciting.
I'm Barbara Oakley, thanks for learning
how to learn.