Daphne Gray-Grant grew up
in the newspaper business.
Her father owned a struggling
weekly paper in Vancouver, Canada.
While going to highschool and
college she worked there until she
graduated and for a few more years.
Then she became a senior editor at a large
metropolitan daily where she worked for
about eight years.
Following that she became
pregnant with triplets and
decided she still didn't
have nearly enough work.
She wanted to be self employed so,
the Publication Coach was born.
Interestingly Daphne says that she
struggled with writers block during all of
her years of newspapering and
didn't address the problem until
she started her own business.
She's also the author of the popular book,
Eight and
a Half Steps to Writing Faster, Better.
Through her website,
www.publicationcoach.com she
offers the weekly newsletter,
Power Writing.
It's weekly, brief, and
best of all, it's free.
I've been a subscriber for years myself
and I encourage you to sign up as well.
Meanwhile, it's my great pleasure
to welcome Daphne here today.
Daphne you're a professional
writing coach.
Tell me about your own past
struggles with writer's block.
Well, you know, the interesting thing for
me is that I struggled enormously with
writing, even when I was a professional
reporter at a daily newspaper.
Now you might think,
how can someone who works at a daily
newspaper have writer's block?
Didn't you have to write every day?
But the thing is, I was a born editor, and
when I worked in newspapers, I did a
little bit of writing and mostly editing.
And I loved editing.
I've always loved editing and
the few times when I had to write when
I worked for the daily newspaper.
I found it very stressful and
extremely difficult.
Partly I guess because I was an editor and
so I was a little bit embarrassed
about how slow a writer I was.
But also because I hadn't
really learned the tricks and
techniques I've since learned to make
writing faster, easier and better.
>> Well, I think we'll be talking
about some of those tricks.
And one of the ways I think that
we might talk about that is just,
how did you teach your triplets to write.
Did you use some of those tricks?
>> [LAUGH] Well, you know,
I taught my triplets to do many things,
they're 20 years old now, and
they're all at university which is great.
They're so different you'd barely know
they were siblings, nevermind triplets.
I don't know whether it would be fair
to say I taught them to write, but
I certainly gave them
some of the tricks and
techniques I give my own clients, and
they too have found them very helpful.
>> Well, let's hone in on one of those tricks.
I mean, how would you describe
the difference between diffuse mode and
focused mode when you're thinking
about and when it comes to writing?
>> Yeah, that's, that's a really,
really important point because, for
me the diffuse mode I call that
the creative or writing mode.
And the focus mode I
call the editing brain.
And what, one of the big mistakes
that many people make when they're
writing is they try to write
with their editing brain.
And the metaphor I like to use is I say,
imagine that these two different
parts of your brain are like two different
people, and now put them in a car.
What do you know about that?
Only one person can drive.
So if you're critical or
focused brain is driving your diffused
brain is asleep in the back seat.
And that's not what anyone
wants when they're writing.
You want your diffused
brain to be active and
awake, to be the one that's
driving when you're writing.
And so one of the techniques I like to
use to help people engage their
diffused brain is mind mapping.
Now the important thing
about mind mapping is
its a little bit different
from concept mapping and I
don't know too much about concept mapping
because I'm not am academic myself.
But mind mapping, which is also
called clustering, some people may
know it by that name instead,
is where you take a piece of paper and
you turn it sideways and
that's really, really important.
Having the paper sideways is essential
because what that does is that kind of
liberates your brain.
And it says oh,
I can go off in any direction.
If you, if you have the paper in
the sort of standard 8.5 by 111 way,
that going to make your brain think you
need to write a list or worse, an outline.
And I really encourage students, in
particular, not to outline before writing.
And I know this flies in the face of
what many Grade 10 English teachers will
counsel you to do but the thing is,
if you think about it,
outlining engages your focused brain.
That's the part of the brain that's good
at spelling and grammar and alphabetical
order and sort of very specific tasks and
when you're writing, you want to create.
You want to think of things.
You want to make new connections.
And that's where you really
need the diffused brain.
So to mind map take that piece of paper,
turn it sideways and
write the topic in the center of the page.
Then draw a circle around it.
And once you've drawn
that circle around it,
then just write whatever
springs into your brain.
The thing I also like to say, and people
find this a little bit gross sometimes,
but I say its kind of like
vomiting onto the page.
[LAUGH] So.
Don't criticize yourself,
don't second guess any of those ideas
that occurs to brain then write it down.
So I did a mind map some years ago and
I use this when I'm teaching
mind mapping all the time.
And I did it on the first day of school.
I, I don't mean I wrote the mind
map on the first day of school.
I wrote the mind map about
the first day of school.
So what I wrote in the center of
the page was first day of school.
And part of the reason I picked
this topic was because it
breaks very neatly into some
obvious marking points.
So one is grade one,
one is high school, one is university.
So you can have different first days
of school tied to those events.
So then I wrote those down and
you'll see I've marked them
with little cross hatches.
I did that after the fact just so
that when you look at the mind
map you can see this easily.
And then if you look you'll see next to
the one I've marked grade one
in the top right hand corner.
I've written the words bee sting.
Now what does a bee sting have to
do with a first day of grade one?
Well, when I went to grade one,
first day of school I'm standing
in the school yard with my mother and
I got stung on the lip by a bee.
I will never ever forget that moment.
For me first day of school will
always be linked with being stung by
a bee right there on the lip.
So all I have to write is two words,
bee sting.
And everything comes back to me.
I can picture the spot, the exact spot
in the playground where I was standing.
I can remember the crabby old
nun who came up to me and
said what are you making such a big
deal about because I was crying.
You know, so
its almost like a movie I can play in my
own brain just based on those two words.
Now one of the questions I often get when
I talk about this is people say well,
I can see how mind mapping
would be very useful for
fiction and I can see how it
might even be useful for memoire.
But what does it have
to do with non fiction?
And I have to say that I use mind
mapping everyday of my writing life and
I have never written any fiction.
Ever.
So I use it entirely for non fiction.
And what you can do is when
you interview someone and
you take your notes,
then you put the notes aside and
you do the mind map based on
your memory of that interview.
And the things that are most interesting,
I guarantee your brain will remember.
Now, for university students,
the issue's going to be a bit different
because you're, it's less likely you're
gong to be interviewing a bunch of people.
It's more likely you're going to
be reading a bunch of books, but
the same principle applies.
If there is something that is really
interesting to you and important and
integral to your research,
you're likely to remember that.
And the things that are most important
are going to float to the top of
your memory.
So you will remember them and
then you can mind map about them.
>> Well, this is very interesting because
it's related to the techniques that
brilliant Nobel Prize winning
neuroscientist Santiago Ramón y Cajal
used when he was trying to
really understand what was going
on at an anatomical level.
He would look very carefully at the cells
he was watching in his microscope, and
then we would turn and
he would try to draw them, and
and he would draw and re-draw.
Until he, he had abstracted
the key chunks that stuck in
his memory from when he was
looking at them with the camera,
with the microscope, versus when he
was trying to draw them on the page.
So in some sense, it seems what
you're doing is, is to try and
abstract the key ideas that
have somehow crystalized in
your mind through using
the mind mapping technique.
>> That, that's a really,
really good way of putting it.
Yeah, and, and, you know,
it's, it interests me.
In terms of education these days,
I think we are down playing
a bit the value of memory.
And, you know, I don't know about you but
I have all my phone numbers
entered into my iPhone.
I don't remember a phone number
anymore to save my life.
And, and people don't memorize
poetry anymore and, you know,
there's all sorts of things that used to
be part of the regular day to day life and
regular school life that aren't there so
much anymore.
And so I think we're a little bit
weary forcing ourselves to rely on our
memory at all.
But the thing that strikes me about
mind mapping is that if something is
interesting or important to you,
you're going to remember it.
At least you're going to remember
it well enough to mind map it.
And then, you know, of course when you
get to the point where you have to
do citations,
of course you have to look it up.
You have to get that 100% right, or
you're, you know, quoting someone else,
you, you need to check it, word for word.
But for doing the mind map, for
inspiring yourself to write, you're
not needing that kind of 100% accuracy,
you're just needing the inspiration.
And that's what mind mapping is so
valuable for.
>> I couldn't agree more and
I also couldn't agree more
about the importance of memory.
I think what we've done is.
Mistakenly by, by thinking,
well, memorization can
be sometimes a bad thing if you're
just sitting there memorizing things
without understanding them, but we've
thrown the baby out with the bath water.
We've said memorization is always bad.
And that's actually not true.
I mean great poets have said memorize
a poem because it helps you to,
to understand the underlying
meaning much more deeply.
And in the same way, when you memorize for
example an equation.
It can help you understand
that poetic under tone
that underlies the equation and,
and that's often lost.
But I have to bring out another something
you've alluded to in the past, and
that's simply the idea of when
you're trying to get into that
diffuse mode and I'm saying this
a little bit metaphorically because we
haven't truly analyzed what's going on.
But, but that, that mode where you're
stepping back a little bit and
you're not focusing completely and
intently.
But and you're trying to get
something down on a page.
That sometimes in order to avoid that
editorial mode, the best thing to do
is to cover up your screen with a,
a towel or something like that.
And that,
that helps prevent you from going back and
trying to edit what you just wrote and
just get it out onto the page.
>> Oh, absolutely.
You know that is the number one mistake.
That most students and
you know, not even students.
You don't have to be a student
to make this mistake.
Most beginning writers make is
they edit while they write.
And I like to say that that's
kind of like trying to
clear the table while
you're still eating dinner.
[LAUGH] It just doesn't work very well and
one of the tricks I suggest to people if
they've developed this habit is that they
turn off their monitor
while they're writing.
So you, of course you need to be a touch
typist to be able to do that, but
if you are a touch typists, then turn of
your monitor and if that feels to drastic,
or if you have a Mac that doesn't let
you turn of your monitor separately,
then just hang a towel over it, and write
without looking at what you're reading.
So, you know, I wrote for
probably 40, more than 40, 40 years.
While I edited constantly while I wrote.
And that was so dysfunctional and
so bad for me, and
it slowed me down so much and
made writing so difficult and
traumatic that I finally made the decision
that I had to break that habit.
And so I started turning off my monitor.
I tried some other things as
well that also really helped.
There's a great app.
Up on the internet called write or die.
So it's write or die dot com.
And if you scroll down
that screen a little bit,
then you'll get to an area where
you can enter the number of
words you want to write and
enter a time limit for yourself.
And then you press a button that says,
I can't remember what it says, but
something like start.
And then you get a blank screen and
you start to write.
And what happens is,
what inevitably happens is we all, will
write a few words and then we stop and
we look off and stare into space while
we're trying to plan what to write next.
And what happens is the software
notices we're not typing and
after X number of seconds,
I think it's about 10 seconds,
of not moving the keyboard at all then,
the screen starts to pinken.
And I like to compare it to a blush.
because the screen's embarrassed for you.
And it gets pinker and pinker and
pinker the longer you go without writing.
And I haven't timed this in a long time so
I can't remember exactly
the time limit it gives you.
Let's say it's 20 seconds.
If you've gone 20 seconds
without writing at
all then you get a loud punishing noise.
So its either a crying baby,
a car alarm, or 70's disco music.
I'll leave it to you to
decide which is worse.
[LAUGH] But its a,
it's a very clever technique for
teaching you to break the habit
of editing while you write.
>> I've used Write or Die myself and
I think it does work very, very well.
I love this approach of separating
your editing from your actual writing.
For me, what I sometimes find is,
when I'm out, I'll think of something and
I'm about to put it down, and
then I think oh, that's terrible.
I, I can't write that and then I'm
editing in my head before I'm writing and
when I stop that, when I just say okay,
I ought to get that out.
Hey, that's terrible, but
that's the way it is.
It's going to come out
on the page terrible.
I'm so surprised later when I look back,
and I find hey, you know what?
That actually wasn't as
terrible as I thought.
In fact, it got me started and,
and it's pretty good.
>> Yes, yes.
That, that happens to so many people.
and, and, you know, I have to tell you,
I have, I've taught writing for
so many years now.
I can tell you that when I talk
to people about that nasty little
editing voice that's in the back of all
our brains, we all have that voice and
it says the same thing to all of us.
It says things like this is no good.
My boss, or teacher,
is going to hate this.
This is boring.
This is really, really bad.
The, that, that voice says really negative
essentially unhelpful things to all of us.
We're all in the same boat.
So what I like to do,
is I like to talk back to that voice.
And I say things like,
could you shut up for a minute?
I don't have time to talk right now.
I will talk to you when I'm editing.
But I'm writing right now, I'm too busy.
And if you can be conscious of
that voice and talk back to it
rather than just let it yammer in
your ear, then you are better off.
So I think the number one technique for
dealing with that, is just recognizing
that it's happening, recognize,
recognizing that it happens to everyone,
and taking some steps to deal with it.
>> Well, I thank you so much, Daphne.
This was so useful, and
a fantastic reminder, even for me.
I want to encourage everyone out there to
please go ahead and explore signing up for
your for Daphne's free newsletter
which is at www.publicationcoach.com.
I'm a subscriber as well.
And maybe even take a look
at her great book Eight and
a Half Steps to writing Faster better or
Daphne's email course which is
called "Extreme Writing Makeover".
So thank you so much again Daphne and
we'll see you on the flip side.
>> Thanks Barb.
Nice talking to you.