Welcome to Learning How to Learn.
My name is Terry Sejnowsky.
Let me introduce you to your brain.
First some brain surgery, we take off the
skull and take out the brain.
This brain weights three pounds, but it
consumes ten times more energy
by weight then the rest of the body, a
very expensive organ.
It is the most complex device in the known
universe.
All of your thoughts, your hopes, your
fears, are in the neurons in this brain.
We price our abilities to do chess and
math but it takes of practice
to acquire these skills and digital
computers
are much better at it than we are.
It came as a surprise to discover that
what we do so well and take
for granted, like seeing, hearing,
reaching, running, are
all much more complex problems than we
thought.
And way beyond the capability of the
world's fastest digital computers.
What this illustrates is that we are not
consciously aware of how our brains work.
Brains evolved to help us navigate complex
environments.
And most of the heavy lifting is done
below our level of consciousness.
And we don't need to know how it's done in
order to survive.
Psychologists who study the unconscious
mind have found
that influences include thought processes,
memory, emotions, and motivation.
We're only aware of a very small fraction
of all the activity in
the brain, so we need to rely on brain
imaging techniques to guide us.
Here is the activity map of someone's
brain who was
asked to lie still, at rest in a brain
imaging scanner.
On the left is the side view of the brain
and on the right is the view from the
mid-line.
The colors indicate brain areas whose
activities were highly correlated, as
shown by the time courses below, color
coded to the brain areas.
The blue areas are highly activity when
the subject
interacts with the world, but turn-off in
the resting state.
The red orange areas are most active in
And are called the default mode network.
The default mode network is a leading
candidate for what we call the focus mode.
When you are quietly studying.
The diffuse mode, which occurs when you
are not
concentrating, may be, not easy to
identify anatomically, but
it is likely to be a shift in the
resting pattern of activity towards a more
coherent global pattern.
Other brightened areas are also more
active
when you are resting, and these areas
can be further divided into groups of
areas that have common patterns of
activity.
This is a new and intense area of
research, and it will
take time to sort out all the resting
states, and their functions.
There are a million, billion synapses in
your brain, where memories are stored.
The old view of the brain is that once it
matures, the strengths of synapses can be
adjusted by learning, but the pattern of
cognitivity
does not change much unless there is brain
damage.
But now we know that brain connectivity is
dynamic and remains so even after it
matures.
With new optical techniques for imaging
single connections between neurons called
synapses,
we can see constant turnover with
new synapses being formed and others
disappearing.
This raises a puzzle.
In the face of so much churn-over, how do
memories stay stable over so many years?
This is a picture of one dendritic branch
on a neuron which receives inputs from
other neurons.
The synapses are the spiny knobs coming
off the dendrite.
On the top the dendrite was imaged before
learning.
The same dendrite is shown below after
learning, and after sleep.
Multiple synapses that are newly formed
together on the
same branch are indicated by the white
arrow heads.
You are looking down into the brain of a
live animal.
This is really a fantastic new technique.
Synapses are less than a micron in
diameter.
In comparison a human hair is around 20
microns in diameter.
This new technique allows us to see how
learning changes the structure of
the brain with a resolution that is near
the limit of light microscopy.
This illustrates that, intriguingly, you
are not the same person
you were after a night's sleep or even a
nap.
It is if you went to bed with one brain
and woke up with an upgrade.
This is a better deal that you can get
from Microsoft.
Shakespeare, the great English poet,
already knew this.
Here is Macbeth lamenting his insomnia.
"Sleep that knits up the ravell'd sleeve of
care.
"The death of each day's life, sore
labour's bath.
"Balm of hurt minds, great nature's second
course.
"Chief nourisher in life's feast."
Here, Shakespeare is making an analogy
between knitted
clothes and sleep that knits up the loose
threads
of experience and concerns during the day
and
weaves them into the tapestry of your life
story.
You will learn, in this first week, how to
take advantage of your unconscious
mind, and also sleep to make it easier to
learn new things and solve problems.
During the lectures you may ask yourself,
how does the brain do this?
A good place to find out more about brain
is the website brainfacts.org.
Brainfacts, one word, .org.
You will find a wealth of interesting
things about
brains and behavior, and in particular
about learning and memory.
I'm Terry Sejnowski.
Happy learning until we meet again.
[BLANK_AUDIO]