[SOUND] When you're learning a new idea,
for example a new vocabulary word.
Or a new concept or a new problem solving
approach.
You sometimes tend to practice it over and
over again during the same study session.
A little of this is useful and necessary,
but continuing to
study or practice after you've mastered
what you can in the session.
Is called overlearning.
Overlearning can have its place, it can
help produce an automaticity that can be
important when you're executing a, a serve
in tennis, or playing a perfect piano
concerto.
If you choke on tests or in
public speaking, overlearning can be
especially valuable.
Did you know that even expert public
speakers practice on the
order of 70 hours for a typical 20 minute
TED Talk?
Automaticity can indeed be helpful in
times of nervousness.
But be wary of repetitive over-learning
during a single session.
Research has shown it can be a waste of
valuable learning time.
The reality is, once you've got the basic
idea
down during a session, continuing to
hammer away at
it during the same session doesn't
strengthen the kinds
of long term memory connections you want
to have strengthened.
Worse yet, focusing on one technique is a
little
like learning carpentry by only practicing
with a hammer.
After a while, you think you can fix
anything by just bashing at it.
Using a subsequent study session to repeat
what you're
trying to learn is just fine, and often
valuable.
It can strengthen and deepen your chunked
neural patterns.
But be wary.
Repeating something you already know
perfectly well is, face it, easy.
It can also bring the illusion of
competence that you've mastered the
full range of material, when you've
actually only mastered the easy stuff.
Instead, you want to balance your studies
by
deliberately focusing on what you find
more difficult.
This focusing on the more difficult
material is called deliberate practice.
It's often what makes the difference
between
a good student and a great student.
All of this is also related to a concept
known as, Einstellung.
In this phenomenon, your initial simple
thought, an
idea you already have in mind or a
neural pattern you've already developed
and strengthened, may
prevent a better idea or solution from
being found.
We saw this in the focus pinball picture,
where your initial pinball thought went to
the upper part of the brain, but the
solution thought pattern was in the lower
part.
The crowded bumpers of the focus mode and
the previous patterns you built can create
a sort
of rut, that prevents you from springing
to
a new place where the solution might be
found.
Incidentally, the German word, Einstellung
means installation.
Basically you can remember einstellung as
installing a roadblock
because of the way you were initially
looking at something.
This kind of wrong approach is especially
easy to
do in sports and science, not to mention
other disciplines.
Because sometimes your initial intuition
about what's happening
or what you need to be doing is
misleading.
You have to unlearn your erroneous older
ideas
or approaches even while you're learning
new ones.
One significant mistake students sometimes
make in learning is
jumping into the water before they learn
to swim.
In other words they blindly start working
on homework without reading the
textbook, attending lectures, viewing
online lessons,
or, or even speaking with someone
knowledgeable.
This is a recipe for sinking, it's like
randomly allowing a thought to kind of pop
off
in the focused mode pinball machine, without
paying
any real attention to where the solution
truly lies.
Understanding how to obtain real solutions
is important in learning and in life.
Mastering a new subject means learning not
only the basic
chunks, but also learning how to select
and use different chunks.
The best way to learn that is by
practicing jumping back and forth [SOUND]
between problems or situations that
require different
techniques or strategies, this is called,
[SOUND] interleaving.
Once you have the basic idea of a
technique down
during your study session sort of like,
learning to ride a
bike with training wheels, start
interleaving your practice with problems
of different types or different types of
approaches, concepts, or procedures.
Sometimes this can be a little tough to
do.
A given section in a book for example is
often devoted to a specific technique so
when you flip to that section, you already
know which technique you're going to be
using.
Still, do what you can to mix up your
learning.
In science and math in particular it can
help to look ahead at
the more varied problem sets that are
sometimes found at the end of chapters.
Or you can deliberately try to make
yourself occasionally pick out
why some problems call for one technique
as opposed to another.
You want your brain to become used to the
idea that just
knowing how to use a particular
concept, approach, or problem-solving
technique isn't enough.
You also need to know when to use it.
Interleaving your studies, making it a
point to review for a
test for example, by skipping around
through problems in the different
chapters and materials, can sometimes seem
to make your learning a
little more difficult, but in reality it
helps you learn more deeply.
Interleaving is extraordinarily important.
Although practice and repetition is
important in helping build solid neural
patterns to draw on, it's interleaving
that starts building flexibility and
creativity.
It's where you leave the world of
practice and repetition and begin thinking
more independently.
When you interleave within one subject or
one discipline,
you begin to develop your creative power
within that discipline.
When you interleave between several
subjects or
disciplines, you can easily, more easily
make interesting
new connections between chunks in the
different
fields, which can enhance your creativity
even further.
Of course it takes time to develop solid
chunks
of knowledge in different fields so
sometimes there's a tradeoff.
Developing expertise in several fields
means you can bring
very new ideas from one field to the
other.
But it can also mean that your expertise
in one field or the other,
isn't quite as deep as that of the person
who specializes in only one discipline.
On the other hand, if you develop
expertise in
only one discipline, you may know it very
deeply, but
you may become more deeply entrenched in
your familiar ways
of thinking, and not be able to handle new
ideas.
Philosopher of science Thomas Kuhn
discovered that
most paradigm shifts in science are
brought
about by either young people, or people
who were originally trained in a different
discipline.
They are not so easily trapped by
einstellung.
Blocked thoughts due to their preceding
training.
And of course there is the old saying that
science progresses one funeral at
a time, as people entrenched in the old
ways of looking at things die off.
Finally don't make the mistake of thinking
that learning only occurs
in the kinds of subjects you acquire from
teachers or books.
When you teach a child how to deal
effectively with a bully, or you fix a
leaky faucet, or you quickly pack a small
suitcase for a business trip to Hong Kong.
All of these illustrate the outcomes of
important aspects of learning.
Physicist Richard Feynman was inspired in
his nobel prize winning work by
watching someone throw a dinner plate into
the air in a cafeteria.
And Mike Rowe of the television show Dirty
Jobs and Somebody's Gotta Do It, shows how
important and exciting learning can be in
a variety of non-academic disciplines.
I'm Barbara Oakley, thanks for learning
about learning.
[BLANK_AUDIO]