[SOUND] In this video I'm going to walk
you through
the basic steps behind how to make a
chunk.
Every discipline is a little different.
Chunking in the subject of history, for
example, is
quite different from chunking in chemistry
or in karate.
In my explanations here, I'm going to lean
a little more
towards explaining chunking of mental
ideas rather than physical body motions.
But you'll see that the two approaches are
closely related.
So, whether you're learning something
mental or
something physical, you'll find some
helpful ideas here.
The first step on chunking is simply to
focus
your undivided attention on the
information you want to chunk.
If you had the television going on in the
background, or you're
looking up every few minutes to check or
answer your phone or computer
messages, it means you're going to have
more difficulty in making a
chunk, because your brain is not really
focusing on chunking the new material.
When you first begin to learn something,
you're making new neural patterns and
connecting them with preexisting patterns
that are
spread through many areas of the brain.
Your octopus tentacles, so to speak, can't
reach very well if some of them are
off on other thoughts using up some of the
limited slots in your working memory.
The second step in chunking is to
understand the basic idea you're trying to
chunk, whether it's understanding a
concept such
as continental drift, seeing the
connection between
the basic elements of the plot for a
story, grasping the economic principle of
supply and demand, or comprehending the
essence
of a particular type of math problem.
Students can often synthesize the gist,
that is
figure out the main idea or ideas, pretty
naturally.
Or at least they can grasp those ideas if
they allow the focused and
diffuse modes of thinking to take turns in
helping them figure out what's going on.
Understanding is like a superglue that
helps hold the underlying memory traces
together.
It creates broad encompassing traces that
can link to other memory traces.
Can you create a chunk if you don't
understand?
Yes, but it's often a useless chunk that
won't fit
in with, or relate to other material of
your learning.
That said, it's important to realize that
just understanding how a problem was
solved, for
example, does not necessarily create a
chunk
that you can easily call to mind later.
Don't confuse the "Aha!", of a breakthrough in
understanding, with solid expertise.
That's part of why you can grasp an idea
when
a teacher presents it in class, but if you
don't review
it fairly soon after you first learned it,
it can
seem incomprehensible when it comes time
to prepare for a test.
In math and science related subjects,
closing the
book and testing yourself on whether you,
yourself,
can solve the problem you think you
understand,
will speed up your learning at this stage.
You often realize the first time you
actually understand
something is when you can actually do it
yourself.
It's the same in many disciplines, just
looking at someone
else's painting doesn't mean you could
actually create that painting
yourself, and just hearing a song won't
give you the
expertise you need to sing it in the same
resonant fashion.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Just because you see it or even that
you
understand it, it doesn't mean that you
can actually do it.
Only doing it yourself helps create
the neural patterns that underlie true
mastery.
The third step to chunking is gaining
context, so you can
see not just how, but also when to use
this chunk.
Context means going beyond the initial
problem and seeing
more broadly, repeating and practicing
with both related and unrelated
problems, so that you can see not only
when
to use the chunk, but when not to use it.
This helps you see how your newly formed
chunk fits into the bigger picture.
In other words, you may have a tool
in your strategy or problem solving tool
box, but
if you don't know when to use that tool,
it's not going to do you a lot of good.
Ultimately, practice helps you broaden the
networks of neurons that are connected to
your chunk, ensuring it's not only firm,
but also accessible from many different
paths.
As you can see from this top down,
bottom up illustration, learning takes
place in two ways.
There's a bottom up chunking process,
where
practice and repetition can help you both
build
and strengthen each chunk, so you can
easily access it whenever you need to.
And there's also a, a sort of a top down
big picture process
that allows you to see what you're
learning and where it fits in.
Both processes are vital in gaining
mastery over the material.
Context is where bottom up and top down
learning meet.
To clarify here, chunking may involve your
learning how to use a certain
problem-solving technique.
Context means learning when to use that
technique instead of some other technique.
Doing a rapid two-minute picture walk
through a
chapter in a book before you begin
studying it,
glancing at pictures and section headings,
can allow
you to gain a sense of the big picture.
So can listening to a very well organized
lecture.
These kinds of activities can help you
know where
to put the chunks you're constructing, how
the chunks
relate to one another, just as you see
here,
with the image of the man in the car.
Learn the major concepts or points first.
These are often the key parts of a good
instructor
or book chapter's outline, flow charts,
tables, or concept maps.
Once you have this done, fill in the
details.
Even if a few of the puzzle pieces are
missing at
the end of your studies, you can still see
the big picture.
So there you go.
Summing it up, chunks are best built
with focused attention, understanding of
the basic idea,
and practice to help you gain mastery and
a sense of the big picture context.
Those are the essential steps in making a
chunk and fitting
that chunk into a greater conceptual
overview of what you're learning.
But there's more.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning how to learn.
[BLANK_AUDIO]