[SOUND] In this video, I'm going to
synthesize
some of the main ideas of this week's
videos.
In other words, we'll chunk our week on
chunking.
Here we go.
Chunks are pieces of information,
neuroscientifically speaking, that
are bound together through use and often
through meaning.
You can think of a chunk as a
scintillating
network of neurons that compactly
synthesizes key ideas or actions.
Chunks can get bigger and more complex.
But at the same time, they're a single
easy to access item that
you can fit like a ribbon into the slot on
your working memory.
Chunks are best built with focused,
undivided attention, understanding of the
basic idea.
And practice to help deepen your patterns
and to help you gain big picture context.
Simple recall, trying to remember the key
points without looking at the
page, is one of the best ways to help the
chunking process along.
It seems to help build neural hooks.
They help you better understand the
material.
Also try recalling material in places that
are different from where you originally
learned the
material, so it becomes more deeply
ingrained
and accessible, regardless of what room
you're in.
This can be very helpful for tests.
Transfer is the idea that a chunk you've
mastered in one area can often help
you much more easily learn chunks of
information
in different areas that can share
surprising commonalities.
Interleave your learning by practicing
your choice of
different concepts, approach, and
techniques all in one session.
Chunks are very important, but they don't
necessarily build flexibility, which
is also important in becoming an expert
with the material you're learning.
Illusions of competence in learning.
Learn to recognize when you're fooling
yourself
about whether you're actually learning the
material.
Test yourself frequently.
Using little mini-tests to see whether
you're actually learning the material, or
whether you've been fooling yourself,
thinking
you're learning when you're actually not.
Recall is actually a form of mini-testing.
Try to avoid depending too much on
highlighting, which can fool you into
thinking that the material is going into
your brain when it actually isn't.
Mistakes are a good thing to make when
you're learning.
They allow you to catch illusions of
competence.
Avoid practicing only the easy stuff,
which can
bring the illusion that you've mastered
the material.
Deliberately practice what you find more
difficult
to gain full mastery of the material.
Einstellung is when your initial thought,
an idea
you've already had in mind, or a neural
pattern you've already developed well and
strengthened, prevents
a better idea or solution from being
found.
Or keeps you from being flexible enough
to accept new, better, or more appropriate
solutions.
The Law of Serendipity is helpful.
Lady Luck favors the one who tries.
Just pick one tiny thing out to learn,
then another.
Just keep trying and you'll be pleasantly
surprised at the results.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning about learning.
[BLANK_AUDIO]