Amy Alkon, is a nationally syndicated
newspaper columnist
radio show host, journalist, book author
and blogger.
She turns reporting on evolutionary
psychology and behavioral science
findings, into
an art form, combining great writing with
deep, yet humorous insight.
The result provides terrific and practical
advice
for how ordinary people can live better
lives.
Amy's books, I See Rude People, and most
recently, Good
Manners for Nice People Who Sometimes Say
the F word.
Has helped create a new genre,
of insightful humor based on practical
science.
Amy may be, as the L.A Weekly put it, Miss
Manners with Things, but I
tend to think of her as the
literary daughter of Charles Darwin, and
Dorothy Parker.
In Amy's work, she's forced to learn fast,
reading a new book every other day
or so, even as she's keeping up with her
voluminous writing and radio show hosting.
She has a great deal of insight about
efficient learning, so
it's a pleasure to speak with her today,
about her work.
Hi Amy, thanks so much for taking time
from your busy schedule.
We know, we both know we're both writers,
that writing
is a form of learning and so what I'd like
to know is, how do use the focused and
diffuse
modes to help you with your writing and
with your learning.
>> I'm normally very focused in my
writing.
It's a very intense process for me, every
hour of writing and so I need to take a
break from that, in order to really have
the information be assimilated into me.
And so, what I like to do is to see that I
work every day little by little.
On a, on a piece of work that I'm doing.
Because then, in the background, when I'm
sleeping, when I'm washing dishes, when
I'm
doing something other than writing, that
information
has a chance to process in my brain.
And that's a very important thing for me.
I used to sometimes wait, until the last
minute to start writing my weekly advice
column.
And this is a huge mistake, because I
would
fail to take advantage of the diffuse mode,
where
I would have these sort of elves in my
brain, taking the information, running
around, doing something with it.
And processing it, instead I would just be
all last minute and I
really wasn't as smart in my writing or my
thinking because of that.
because I didn't have that extra time.
And it wasn't actual so much it wasn't
that I spent so much time, doing
extra work it was just doing it days ahead
of time that really made a difference.
>> That sounds like a lot like the way I
approach writing as well.
Well tell me this, what do you do to help
prevent procrastination when
you have the kind of writing job that you
really rather not be doing.
>> Well all writing jobs are jobs I'd
rather not be doing.
It sometimes you have a beautiful
paragraph, it just goes
like butter, it's wonderful, it's funny,
it's all together and clear.
But usually that's not the case.
And so usually knowing that, I would
rather do just about anything than write.
This is the time I sit down to write and
I think about lint that must be lurking
behind my furniture.
So, what I do is I turn on a timer.
I set the timer for an hour, I
know other people use different, different
times 20 minutes,
the Pomodoro but I like the hour because
that gives me enough time to get into
flow.
A flow state where I, maybe can lose
myself in the work.
And sometimes I'll get going and I just
feel dumb and like
I'm making no progress, but I start typing
and I start thinking
and eventually something will come and I
usually do get to that
state where I get lost in my work and
something really wonderful happens.
But you really need to put in that time
like that.
And not go clean behind your furniture in
order to make the work really work.
>> You keep a very fast paced reading
schedule, on
top of your regular work, that many people
would find daunting.
How do you do it and do you have any
special advice for picking out and
remembering key points in books?
>> Well one of the really important things
I learned.
I used to read whole books even if they
were boring and terrible.
And I was reading War and Peace and every
other chapter, Napoleon is there, they're
cold, they're feet are wet, and it would,
these, these chapters were just boring to
me.
So I realized it's okay to skip parts of
books, and
so now, I approach a book like I do a
buffet.
And I, I take the things from it that are
important
to me and I skip, I skip the parts that
are not.
So, when I say I read probably a book a
night, but I don't read the whole book in
every case.
Some of them I just open and I see they're
not worth very much and I close them right
away.
But I think it's very important to even
when you're reading
a chapter, if you see a story you've
already read it.
If you read a lot of science you, you'll
read research that you've read a million
times before.
I just, lop that off the chapter and move
on
to the stuff that I don't know and haven't
read.
I think it's really important to be a
critical reader in that way.
And then, the other question you asked me.
So you asked how do.
What was the second question?
Sorry.
>> [LAUGH] Do you have any special advice
for picking out and remembering key points
in books?
>> Well, there aren't so many key points
in books.
And sometimes when a book is very
important to me or a point is very important.
What I'll do is I'll write it down.
It's really important, writing something
down with
an actual pen and ink, remember those?
it, it seems to ingrain it into your brain
better.
And then what I do, and this maybe seems
funny, I tape it on the wall outside my
shower.
And I can see it from when I'm in there.
And so, I can look at that idea when I'm
there and this is sort of a diffuse mode
of thinking.
I'm not really focused on it and I'm not
as intense
as I am when I'm reading the book, but
it's just there.
So, I can think about it in a sort of less
intense way and, and
it helps me ingrain an idea that maybe is
a difficult idea to,otherwise, get.
>> Any particular tips on how you learn
most efficiently?
>> I will when I read a passage that I
don't quite get, I'll read it a
few times because sometimes the first
time, you miss
things or it's the language you're not
used to.
So that's pretty important.
Another thing I'll do, is go to other
reference material.
Because sometimes someone is a poor
writer, but has some really good ideas.
So if I can understand the things they
don't
explain well, then I can maybe understand
their idea better.
>> That makes sense.
finally, do you have any tips related to
sleep.
I love sleep.
I do about six things well, and one of
them is napping.
And this was not always the case.
I took a yoga class, which I, I hate yoga,
it
was horrible, but the thing I learned to
do was to breathe.
I learned to slow down my breathing.
And so, in order to sleep.
I just slow down my breathing.
I'll take, ten really really slow breaths,
and I use that to slow myself down
so I can fall asleep and something very
important is not to sleep for too long.
Because if you sleep for too long, you can
actually get groggy.
So, I set my alarm clock for about 30
minutes and about five minutes of that
is getting my dog to come down, because
she sleeps with her little snout on my
neck.
And she's only five pounds.
She's not a Great Dane.
[LAUGH] So, I, I then sleep for maybe 20
minutes, which seems
to be a very good amount of time to give
you a reboot.
Rather than make you groggy.
>> That all sounds great, and Amy, thank
you so very much for all of these
insights.
I'm sure they'll be particularly helpful
for the writers among us.
So thank you so very much.