[SOUND].
This week, we're going to be talking about
chunks, compact
packages of information that your mind can
easily access.
We'll talk about how you can form chunks,
how you can use them to improve your
understanding of, and creativity with the
material, and
how chunks can help you do better on
tests.
We'll also talk about illusions of
competence in learning.
This was when you're using ineffective
study methods that fool your mind
into thinking you're learning something
when you're mostly just wasting your time.
We'll cover what those less effective
study methods are and tell you what
methods research has shown will work
better to help you in your studies.
Finally we'll talk about something called
overlearning, which
can solidly ingrain information in your
mind, but also
can be a little like digging deeper ruts
as you might spin your wheels
ineffectively in learning.
You can make your study time more valuable
by interleaving, providing intelligent
variety in your studies.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning how to learn.