Scott Young is the ultimate
adventurer in learning.
He's compressed the entire
four year MIT curriculum for
computer science into one year
of independent learning, and is
now wrapping up a year's travel, learning
four different languages, Spanish,
Portuguese, Chinese, and Korean through
total immersion in each of the countries.
Scott doesn't just study learning
from an academic perspective.
He immerses himself in learning and
perceptively observes the results so
that we can all gain from it.
So, it's a pleasure to
welcome Scott Young.
Scott, I'm always excited
to follow your adventures.
So tell me, where are you now and
what is your latest learning challenge?
>> Right.
So right now at the moment I'm actually in
South Korea, in Seoul not too
far away from Gangnam actually.
And I am learning Korean.
And this is part of a larger project where
a friend and I are traveling for a year.
Staying three months in
four different countries.
So three months each trying
to learn the language of
that country through not speaking
English as much as possible.
>> Wow.
I'm just so impressed.
You're sort of a Marco Polo of learning.
[LAUGH] And I was also impressed
by your MIT challenge in learning.
What you did was you compressed a four
year curriculum of computer science into
one year of independent learning.
There are a lot of questions I have for
you in relation to that experience as well
as your language learning experience.
So first, can you tell us, how do you
avoid illusions of competence in learning?
>> Right.
Well, I'm a big fan of trying to dive
into a position where you might
be wrong as soon as possible.
So, when you're just reading a lecture,
reading a textbook,
you can't ever really be wrong.
There's no real check on
whether you know what you know.
And, I really like getting into problems
as quickly as possible with a language,
trying to speak as quickly as possible.
Or if not speaking quick as
quickly as possible testing my,
my listening comprehension in a,
in a, in a strict way.
So, with the MIT challenge I,I
would work on problem sets.
And I would do my best to do the problem
sets without having the solutions at hand.
And try my best on, on any problem and
if I got stuck, if I couldn't finish,
then of course go to the problem and
check to see the solution and learn it.
But I think only if you feel
that grind a bit first,
if you feel that tension, that stress that
you're not quite sure how to finish it
only then will you really remember
how to do the problem for the future.
So if you don't have that feeling
of not being sure how to do it and
that strain, I think it is hard
to really improve your knowledge.
>> But that goes right along with
our own learning philosophy.
In this course which is test
yourself as frequently as possible.
So, one of the approaches that
you have to learning that I
absolutely love is that
of self explanation.
Can you explain to our viewers a little
bit what you mean by self explanation?
What, what is it and
what kind of benefits can you get from it?
>> Right, well I got this idea
reading biography of Richard Feynman.
He was a Nobel Prize winning physicist,
and
I forget the exact method that he used
himself, but I remember him talking about,
you know, being a Nobel prize
winner in theoretical physics.
He's a smart guy, and he was talking
about a particular academic paper,
a particular concept he didn't understand.
And his approach wasn't
to throw his hands up and
say, well, you know,
I don't get it or, it's too difficult.
But he want through meticulously, not
only trying to understand everything that
was in that paper, but
of the papers it sourced.
He read through them very carefully and
combed through them and, and
tried to make sure he understood
all the supporting ideas.
So, for me, I've kind of adapted that into
this idea of taking a blank piece of paper
out and writing as if I'm trying to teach
someone else what this idea is all about.
Or what this process for solving
a particular type of problem is all about.
Or what it means.
And what I find happens is that you
usually get to points where you
have some friction,
where you have to be too vague or
you can't really be as exact and
precise as you want to be.
And those are usually the things
that you don't understand.
So you can go back to your notes,
you can go back to the textbook,
look up that exact spot, and figure out,
oh, this is the part I'm missing.
I'm missing step three of this process.
Or I don't really understand
why step three works,
maybe I can ask someone,
a teacher or a, or a friend.
>> I think it's so
smart to go look and intuit how
other very creative people have,
have approached their problem solving.
And I always love Feynman's approach.
He always said that,
that it's very important that, that
the first rule is not to fool yourself,
but you are the easiest person to fool.
So I, I, I just love how you're,
you're learning from other learners.
Can you, can you
one of your approaches that I really
like is that of creating vivid examples.
Can you give us an example of that?
>> So, the mind doesn't learn
abstract things very well.
It works a lot better when you
have something very concrete,
you can point to it and say,
oh, this is how it works.
And, math and science is often full of
things that are just pure abstract,
abstraction, they, they only connect very
loosely to things we can touch and feel.
So what I try to do is find simple
analogies that are, are metaphors and
try to test them or see how to make them
fit with the thing I'm trying to learn.
So it's kind of like looking
through your mind for examples or
stories or things that you
are familiar with, and like, fitting
a jigsaw piece into a puzzle, trying
to figure out, what's the right piece.
So I'll give you a quick example of that.
I was learning about electricity and
one of the concepts you
learn early on is voltage.
Now, I didn't have a good
intuition of what voltage was.
So I'm trying to make a, a mental
picture of what voltage could be, and
I'm thinking about, you know,
an electrical circuit.
Well, it's a little bit
like pipes with water.
And so if, if the electrical
circuits like pipes with water,
then what are all of the components?
And current is pretty easy.
Well, that's like the water flowing.
I, I can get that.
But what was voltage, and I was like,
what was it like pressure?
But if you look at the equations for
pressure and you look at the equations for
voltage, they don't really look alike so
that, that felt wrong.
And I realize that, you know,
if you've studied electricity,
you've usually also studied the, the,
the, the gravity beforehand, and
what was the same was electric
potential and gravitational potential.
So, oh, voltage is like height.
So I can imagine in my head
that the high voltage wires
are like pipes that are physically
higher than the other pipes.
So the way water when it rushes down,
when it goes down from the high level to
the low level, it gives off a lot
more energy because it's falling.
And that metaphor really helped
me because not only was it
something concrete that I'll never forget,
but it also was fairly accurate.
And then I tested out a couple things
like pressure and I found, okay,
this is the one that works.
And sometimes, this process
can take a little bit of time.
I'm recapping this in two seconds, but
it really took me about an hour to comb
through the notes to figure this one out.
But.
You can ask professors, you can ask,
you know, hey, is this kind of like this?
And someone who really
understands can help you out.
Or you can just do what I did and just
try to fit different puzzle pieces and
see what fits.
Because even if you don't
find a good puzzle piece,
you can still learn a lot more that way.
>> Oh I, I couldn't agree more.
I do find that as the years have gone by,
the most creative professors who
I've worked with, researchers, are always
the ones who use these kinds of analogies.
And the ones who are more pedantic,
a little more by the book,
often aren't as creative about
how they approach things.
So I think that's a very intelligent
way of, of going at everything.
Can you talk to our viewers just
a little bit about motivation?
How can you develop a passion for
learning, perhaps even in subjects you
think you don't have a passion for?
Any suggestions for
mental tools people can use to help
motivate themselves in their learning?
>> Well, I love this question, because
right now I'm learning languages, and
we're currently, I'm currently learning
my sixth language, Korean right now.
And we're doing it in very
tight time constraints.
So I've gotten a few emails
from people who have,
you know, heard about the project,
and they said, well, maybe you and
your friend who were doing this have
this natural talent for languages and,
you know, this, this genetic gift.
And I think it's so
funny, because I remember, the first time
I was trying to learn a foreign language,
French, I spent about the same
amount of time I'm spending here.
And I barely passed the exam.
[LAUGH] I got a D.
And I'm, I feel like I'm a fairly
smart fellow in other things.
So I didn't really let it get to me.
But I think, it's true for
a lot of subjects.
That, being intelligent within
that subject is often a factor,
just how much exposure you've had to it.
So if you're not used to math, don't take
that as a sign that maybe you're bad at
math, but
just that you need to put more time in.
And you'll get more motivation, it'll
be even more easy to motivate yourself,
you'll have more interest
once you're better at it.
And you can get better at it by,
by encouraging yourself to take on
little steps, little mini projects.
And once you complete that project,
you build more confidence.
With more confidence, you can do more
things, you can understand more things and
it becomes more interesting.
And I just, I love your story that
you gave of, of learning math,
because I think that's
just a perfect example and
it's too bad that a lot of people just
don't conceptualize the world that way.
One thing that I really like about
your own story is, you failed, but
you just learned from failure.
You didn't allow that to get to you.
You just sort of shifted
your strategies and
figured out what strategy
was more successful.
And I think that's a sign of
the best learners, is not to be set,
set back by failure,
they just learn from it.
>> Absolutely.
>> So, I, I love how you've developed
projects for self education.
Can you tell us a little more about
what you've done this way and
how our viewers might go about developing
their own projects for self education?
>> Right, so I actually got
this idea from a good friend.
He's also in, I think,
your recommended resources, Benny Lewis.
And he was someone who told me I
remember he told me in person one day,
he's like, always have a mission.
And basically just this idea of, he, he
would pick these three month missions for
learning languages, because that was
usually how long he could secure a tourist
visa [LAUGH] to this place to try to learn
as much as possible in three months.
But it really struck me how different
that was from the regular approach.
The regular approach of going, and you
know, I'm going to just learn this and I
don't really have any concrete goals and I
don't really have any specific motivation.
And of course it tapers off and
you don't achieve that much.
And what I found really helpful is
making very concrete projects that
are exciting to me.
Something that, you know,
this is really interesting.
So when I did the MIT Challenge,
just this idea kind of obsessed me.
This idea of, you know, would it be
possible to learn the things that
an MIT student would learn in
school without going to MIT?
Or this language learning project,
you know.
Would it be possible to get to
a conversational level, or, or a decent
amount of level through complete immersion
in four different countries in a year?
So I, I tend to pick these
kind of grand projects.
But I think you could pick
something very simple.
You could just say, you know,
I want to try learning this over a month.
And I'm going to obsess about it and
make it interesting.
And that's often how you can turn
something that might otherwise be
dull into something that fascinates you,
because it's this specific
concrete challenge.
>> I like this approach.
It seems very similar to what I did
with helping to create this MOOC.
So, yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Any tips on effective
use of online resources?
Right.
So,
this is I think particularly relevant
to your audience, because you know,
a MOOC audience you're signed up
to this through Co, Coursera and
you probably know about Coursera and
edX and all of the great MOOC platforms.
And I really think these platforms
are the future because they
have such high quality courses,
but it's still early days.
And I think that there's still a lot
of subjects that people would like to
learn but maybe there isn't a MOOC for it.
And I think there's also
some disadvantages to MOOCs.
In particular if you want to
learn something a little bit
more advanced MOOCs can sometimes be a bit
harder because they tend to be written for
audience with no prerequisites,
no requirements.
So you might feel that if you wanted
to do, you know, some physics it
isn't just an intro physics class, this
is a little bit harder, because you know,
they are expecting that I
haven't learned calculus or
I haven't learned something different.
And so what I recommend is using
MIT's open course ware's incredible.
It has literally hundreds, I don't know
whether it has thousands of courses, but
it has just such a huge volume of courses.
And sometimes the courses aren't
really well supported, like they
don't have videos, they don't have,
it's not as hands-on as, as these MOOCs.
But I've found sometimes what they'll have
is they'll have the exams in the problem
sets and a list of the readings,
and a link to a textbook.
I can buy the textbook used on Amazon for
$15 sometimes.
And I'd get it delivered, and
I would do it, and honestly I felt like I
sometimes learned more from those
courses than the video lecture courses.
So I think if you are willing
to be bit more adventurous,
there's literally almost no topic
you can't learn through this kind of
structured, university-like format
through the resources available online.
>> It's an explosion in
learning how to learn.
I mean this, the what's available now to
the public is just absolutely phenomenal.
And so anyone who has an interest
in pretty much anything can,
can do some great exploration.
So as our, our wrap up question here,
you've written that you,
you can learn more by studying less.
What do you mean by that?
>> All right, so
I think you've touched on it a lot
in this course that you're offering.
That people get caught up in low
efficiency, low intensity studying habits,
and because they learn a lot slower
with those methods they end up
spending a lot more time studying.
And because they're spending
a lot more times studying,
which is naturally more tiring, you go
into less efficient studying methods.
It's a little bit like exercising.
It's as if, you know, you're not getting
the exercise results you want, so
you extend your workout
from one hour to two hour.
But now you're not working out as,
more intensely, so you make it four hours.
And now, you know, you really can't do
more than just a light jog for four hours,
or maybe just walking.
And eventually,
it eats up all of your time.
But you're, you're not having
the intensity that your muscles in
your body really need to
get physical improvement.
And similarly, I think the same
is true with mental improvement.
So what I try to do is,
I try to pick specific chunks
of time that I'm going to study.
And they don't have to be too big.
So right now, I'm learning Korean
over at least three months.
And I'm actually only doing
three to four hours a day.
Of studying time,
which is considerably less than I
would say a typical full-time
student studying Korean.
But I think that I've been
making quite good progress just
because the actual time I'm
spending is highly focused.
This kind of test yourself feedback so
that I'm using things like Anki for
flashcards.
And I'm doing actual conversations
one-on-one with a tutor.
And these things are very efficient,
but they are also very intense.
But the benefit of that is that you have
more time and you can relax outside of it.
>> Great advice and as always,
great advice from you.
I know I've learned a lot and really
enjoyed following your adventures and,
and getting new tips on learning from you.
So I thank you so much, Scott.
And we'll see you on the flip side.
>> Well, thank you very much for
letting me be a part of this.
I, I really hope the students taking
this course found some value in it,
the video I put together.