[SOUND] The ability to combine chunks in
new and original
ways underlies a lot of historical
innovation.
Bill Gates and other industry leaders set
aside extended week-long reading
periods so that they can hold many and
varied ideas in mind during one time.
This helps generate their own innovative
thinking by allowing fresh
in mind not yet forgotten ideas to network
amongst themselves.
Basically what people do to enhance their
knowledge and gain expertise
is to gradually build the number of chunks
in their mind.
Valuable bits of information, they can
piece together in new and creative ways.
Chess masters, for example, can easily
access thousands of different chess
patterns.
Musicians, linguists and scientists can
each access
similar chunks of knowledge in their own
disciplines.
The bigger and more well practiced your
chunked mental library, whatever the
subject you're
learning, the more easily you'll be able
to solve problems and figure out
solutions.
As we'll discover soon, chunking isn't all
you'll
need to develop creative flexibility in
your learning.
But it's an important component.
Chunks can also help you understand new
concepts.
This is because when you grasp one chunk,
you'll find that that chunk can be related
in surprising ways to similar chunks, not
only
in that field, but also in very different
fields.
This idea is called transfer.
For example, concepts and problems solving
methods you learned for
physics can be very similar to chunked
concepts in business.
I've found some aspects of language
learning were very helpful
for me when I later began to learn
computer programming.
A chunk is a way of compressing
information much more compactly.
As you gain more experience in chunking in
any particular subject,
you'll see that the chunks you're able to
create are bigger.
In some sense that the ribbons are longer.
Not only are those ribbons longer, but the
neural patterns are in some sense darker.
They're, they're more solid and firmly
ingrained.
If you have a library of
concepts and solutions internalized as
chunked patterns,
you can think of it as a collection or a
library of neural patterns.
When you're trying to figure something
out, if
you have a good library of these chunks,
you
can more easily skip to the right solution
by
metaphorically speaking, listening to
whispers from your diffuse mode.
Your diffuse mode can help you connect two
or
more chunks together in new ways to solve
novel problems.
Another way to think of it is this.
As you build each chunk, it is filling in
a part of your larger knowledge picture.
But if you don't practice with your
growing chunks, they can remain faint, and
it's harder to put together the big
picture of what you're trying to learn.
In building a chunked library, you're
training your brain
to recognize not only a specific concept,
but different types
and classes of concepts so that you can
automatically
know how to solve quickly or handle
whatever you encounter.
You'll start to see patterns that simplify
problem solving for you and will
soon find that different solution
techniques are
lurking at the edge of your memory.
Before midterms or finals it can be easy
to
brush up and have these solutions at the
mental ready.
There are two ways to figure something out
or to solve problems.
First there's sequential step by step
reasoning,
and second through a more holistic
intuition.
Sequential thinking, where each small step
leads
deliberately towards a solution, involves
the focused mode.
Intuition on the other hand often seems to
require this
creative diffuse mode linking of several
seemingly different focused mode thoughts.
Most difficult problems and concepts are
grasped through intuition, because these
new ideas make a leap away from what
you're familiar with.
Keep in mind that the diffuse mode's semi
random way of making connections means
that the solutions they provide should be
very carefully verified using the focused
mode.
Intuitive insights aren't always correct.
You may think there are so many problems
and concepts, just in a single
section or chapter of whatever you're
studying,
there's just no way to learn them all.
This is where the law of serendipity comes
into play.
Lady luck favors the one who tries.
Just focus on whatever section you're
studying.
You'll find that once you put that first
problem or concept in your mental library,
whatever it is, then the second concept
will go in a little more easily.
And the third more easily still.
Not that all of this is a snap, but it
does get easier.
I am Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning about learning.
[BLANK_AUDIO]