Welcome back.
It is hard to learn when
you're not into it.
But if it's something you're really
interested in, learning is easy.
Why is that?
Most of the neurons in your cortex
carry information about what
is happening around you and
what you're doing.
Your brain also has a set of diffusely
projecting systems of neuromodulators,
that carry information not about
the content of an experience but
it's importance and value to your future,
neuromodulators are chemicals that
influence how a neurons
responds to other neurons.
And today we will discuss three of them.
Acetylcholine, dopamine and serotonin.
Acetylcholine neurons form
neuromodulatory connections to
the cortex that
are particularly important for
focused learning,
when you are paying close attention.
These acetylcholine
neurons project widely and
activate circuits that
control synaptic plasticity.
Leading to new long term memory.
Neuromodulators also have a profound
impact on your unconscious mind.
One of the great brain discoveries
in my lifetime has been that our
motivation is controlled by a particular
chemical substance called Dopamine.
Which is found in a small set of neurons
in our brain stem shown here in orange.
These dopamine neurons are part of a large
brain system that controls reward learning
and in particular in the basal ganglia
which is located in the green region above
the dopamine neurons and
below the cortex at the top of the brain.
Dopamine is released from these neurons,
when we receive an unexpected reward.
Dopamine signals project widely and
have a very powerful effect on learning.
And this is something that
also affects decision making.
And even the value of sensory inputs.
Dopamine is in the business of
predicting future rewards and
not just the immediate reward.
This can motivate you to do something
that may not be rewarding right now but
will lead to a much better
reward in the future.
Addictive drugs artificially
increase dopamine activity and
fool your brain into thinking that
something wonderful has just happened.
In fact just the opposite
has just happened.
This leads to craving and dependence,
which can hijack your free will and
can motivate actions
that are harmful to you.
Loss of Dopamine neurons leads
to a lack of motivation.
And something called anhedonia,
which is a loss of interest in
things that once gave you pleasure.
Severe loss of Dopamine
neurons causes resting tremor,
slowness, rigidity,
this is called Parkinson's disease.
Ultimately it leads to catatonia,
a complete lack of any movement.
Dopamine neurons are part of
the unconscience part of your brain.
That you learned about in the first week.
When you promise to treat
yourself something after a study
section you are tapping
into your dopamine system.
Serotonin is a third diffuse neuromodulatory system
that strongly affects your social life.
In monkey troops the alpha male has the
highest level of serotonin activity and
the lowest ranking male
has the lowest levels.
Prozac, which is prescribed for
clinical depression,
raises the level of Serotonin activity.
The level of Serotonin is also closely
linked to risk taking behavior.
With higher risk in
lower Serotonin monkeys.
Inmates in jail for
violent crimes have some of the lowest
levels of serotonin activity in society.
Finally your emotions strongly affect
learning as you are well aware.
Emotions were once thought to
be separate from cognition but
recent research has shown that emotions
are intertwined with perception and
attention and
interact with learning and memory.
The amygdala an almond shaped structure
shown here, nestled down at the base of
the brain is one of the major
centers where cognition and
emotion are effectively integrated.
The amygdala is part of the limbic system
which together with hippocampus is
involved in processing memory and
decision making as well as
regulating emotional reactions.
You will want to keep your amygdala
happy to be an effective learner.
The emotions and your neuromodulatory systems are slower than perception and
action but are no less important for
successful learning.
If you want to learn more about
Acetylcholine, Dopamine, and
Serotonin, look them on brainfacts.org.
A website that is filled with
valuable facts about your brain.
I'm Terry Sejnowski.
Happy learning, until we meet again.