In this video, we're going to give you
a little background about how to make a
chunk.
If you're learning to play a difficult
song on the guitar, the neural
representation
of the song in your mind can be considered
as a rather large chunk.
You would first listen to the song.
Maybe you'd even watch someone else
playing the song especially if you were
just a beginner who was learning things
like, how to hold the guitar.
Getting an initial sense of the pattern
you want to
master for yourself is similar for most
subjects or skills.
You often have to grasp little bits of
songs that become
neuro mini-chunks, which will later join
together into larger chunks.
For example, over several days, you might
learn how to smoothly
place the musical passages on a guitar,
and when you've grasped
those passages, you could join them
together with other passages that
you've learned, gradually putting
everything together
so you can play the song.
In learning a sport, say basketball,
soccer, golf.
You grasp and master various bits and
pieces of the skills you need.
You're creating little neural mini-chunks,
that you
can then gradually knit together into
larger neural chunks.
Later you can hit those larger chunks into
still larger
and more complex chunks that you can draw
up in
an instant, in reaction to say to a
slight, shift
and twist in a soccer ball that's coming
your way.
The best chunks are the ones that are so
well ingrained, that
you don't even have to consciously
think about connecting the neural pattern
together.
That, actually, is the point of making
complex
ideas, movements or reactions into a
single chunk.
You can see this in language learning.
In the beginning often just saying a
single word with the
proper nuance, tone and accent involves a
lot of practice.
Stringing extemporaneous sentences together
involves the ability to creatively
mix together various complex mini-chunks
and chunks in the new language.
To see what I mean, try repeating the
following tongue-twister in the Indian
language of Kannada.
>> Hi, I am Shilpa Konkani.
I am native speaker of Kannada which is
one of the oldest language spoken in
India.
Today, I'm going share you a
tongue-twister in Kannada.
So let's get started.
Terikere yri male muru kari kurimari meyuthiddavu.
>> Not easy, is it?
Unless you are a native
speaker of Kannada,
but the language was
learned bit by bit.
Learning in math and science involves the
same approach.
When you're learning new math and science
material,
you're often given sample problems with
worked out solutions.
This is because, when you're first trying
to understand how
to work a problem, you have a heavy
cognitive load.
So it helps to start out with a work
through example.
It's like first listening to a song before
trying to play the song yourself.
Most of the details of the work out
solution are right there, and your
job is simply to figure out why the steps
are taken the way they are.
They can help you see the key features,
and underline principles of a problem.
One concern about using worked out
examples in math and science to help you
in starting to form chunks, is that it can
be all too easy to focus too
much on why an individual step works and
not on the connection between steps.
That is,
On why this particular step is the next
thing you should do.
So keep in mind that I'm not just talking
about
a cookie-cutter, just-do-as-you're told,
mindless
approach when following a worked-out
solution.
It's more like using a road map to help
you when traveling to a new place.
Pay attention to what's going on around
you when you're using the
map, and soon you'll find yourself able to
get there on your own.
You'll even be able to figure out new ways
of getting there.
Next, we'll walk you through the actual
steps of chunk formation.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning how to learn.
[MUSIC]
#Hey little girl sometimes the times get
hard but soon
#the storm will pass and you'll be playing
in the yard.
#Hey little girl sometimes you might feel
sad but some
#day you'll realize it really ain't that
bad. Just part of growing up.#
[MUSIC]